<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The abominations of the Church of Rome discovered in a recantation-sermon lately preached in the French church of the Savoy : whereunto are added many curious particulars of the practices of the papists beyond the seas / by Franc. de La Motte ... ; English'd.</title>
            <title>Motifs de la conversion à la religion reformée. English</title>
            <author>La Motte, François de.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 222 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 65 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A49156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L303</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8201</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12922490</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12922490</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95424</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A49156)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95424)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 387:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The abominations of the Church of Rome discovered in a recantation-sermon lately preached in the French church of the Savoy : whereunto are added many curious particulars of the practices of the papists beyond the seas / by Franc. de La Motte ... ; English'd.</title>
                  <title>Motifs de la conversion à la religion reformée. English</title>
                  <author>La Motte, François de.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 120 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by W.G. and are to be sold by Moses Pitt ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Translation of: Motifs de la conversion à la religion reformée.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95424:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95424:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Abominations OF THE CHURCH of ROME: Diſcovered in A RECANTATION-SERMON, Lately Preached in the <hi>FRENCH</hi> Church of the <hi>Savoy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto are added many Curious Particulars, of the Practices of the</hi> PAPISTS <hi>beyond the Seas.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>BY <hi>FRANC. DE LA MOTTE,</hi> Late Preacher of the Order of the <hi>CARMELITES,</hi> newly Converted to the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>ENGLISH'D.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed by <hi>W. G.</hi> and are to be ſold by <hi>Moſes Pitt,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Angel</hi> over-againſt the little North door of St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1675.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Where you may likewiſe have the ſame in</hi> French, <hi>as it was Preached.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:95424:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95424:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONORABLE, S<hi rend="sup">R</hi> 
               <hi>JOSEPH WILLIAMSON,</hi> One of His MAJESTIES moſt Honorable Privy Council, and Principal Secretary of State.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIGHT HONORABLE,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>IF I were not fully perſwaded of Your kind acceptance of theſe Sheets, I ſhould not be ſo bold to offer them to Your Honour: But the ſenſible expreſſions of Your great goodneſs and favour which I have already received, and the Approbation with which You were pleaſed to honor this Diſcourſe when it came out of the Pulpit, at the time of my <hi>Recantation,</hi> will not ſuffer me to doubt, but that You will accept of it alſo now that it comes out of the Preſs.</p>
            <p>I hope it will not be unſerviceable in this Nation, to ſettle in the profeſſion of the Truth the wavering minds of many too much inclinable to Popery: This Conſideration, with the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities of my Auditors, have prevailed upon me to publiſh theſe lines: which I deſire may be look'd upon as a teſtimony of the ſincere pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
<pb facs="tcp:95424:3"/>of my Faith, and of that Loyalty and Obedience, which I do hereby vow to the Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Monarch of theſe Noble Kingdoms, where I am come to ſeek for a ſhelter. I might with reaſon expect to find it amongst <hi>Proteſtants;</hi> but the inſolency and inſulting humour of the Party that I forſake, and the affronts that I have already met with, even in the streets, ſince my profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, force me to flie to the Protection of Your Honour; whoſe extraordinary Abilities and Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delity have given You ſo near an acceſs to His moſt Excellent Majeſty, and cauſe You to act ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily in that noble station, unto which Your own deſervings and Your Prince's favour have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted You.</p>
            <p>Your Generoſity and Goodneſs will, I hope, pardon my preſent boldneſs, as proceeding from a thankfull acknowledgement of Your former favours, and from an earneſt deſire to be eſteem'd, as really I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Right Honorable,</salute>
               <signed>Your Honour's moſt humble, moſt obedient, and moſt obliged Servant, <hi>FRANCIS de la MOTTE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:95424:3"/>
            <head>To the READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>CHRISTIAN READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Might very well have excuſed my ſelf in not yielding to the earneſt requeſts of ſeveral Eminent Perſons, who have again and again deſired this pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lication, if I had regarded either the common unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs of Writers, eſpecially ſuch as offer to meddle with Religion, or the cenſures and hatred of my former Friends, which this will infallibly draw upon me. But I intend not to be much concerned at the Sayings of thoſe, who are engaged by their Vows to ſpurn at every thing that diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>agrees with their Superſtition, who are wont to condemn a Book at the ſight of the Title, and to execute it in the fire before they have peruſed it. I have conſidered, that their diſpleaſure alone ſhould not hinder me from giving this to the Preſs, becauſe I am certain that others more impartial and leſs prejudicated, will vouchſafe unto it their favourable conſtruction; ſeeing that it may prove to be uſeful to ſuch as are blinded with errour, by diſcovering to them the Truth. Beſides, in regard ſome have been pleaſed to ſurmiſe that I did not dare to publiſh many of thoſe things which I mentioned a month ago in the <hi>French</hi> Church of the <hi>Savoy,</hi> at the time of my Abjuration, ſaying, that they were falſe Inventions, becauſe I named neither the places nor the perſons guilty of thoſe diſorders, of which I did then accuſe the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and that I had made its Authors and Doctors ſpeak that which they never intended, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I have thought my ſelf obliged
<pb facs="tcp:95424:4"/>in vindication of my Credit to reveal and declare their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies in a larger Diſcourſe, ſo that they themſelves may now perceive, that they were not a little engaged to me for my ſparing them ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>much, for I might with juſtice have ſaid a great deal more. They might have conſidered, that I was then in a place where it is not uſual to ſpeak all that is known, and that the reſpect which I have yet for many of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Clergy, of whoſe hands I have received many perſonal favours, did hinder me from the diſcovery of all their nakedneſs.</p>
            <p>But ſeeing they are ſo earneſt with me to deſire me to ſhew them the paſſages which I alledged out of St. <hi>Bernard, Baronius, Bellarmine,</hi> and others, and to name the places where the grievous abuſes concerning the Worſhip of Images and the Relicks of the Saints have been ſeen, I cannot deny their requeſt; for it may be God intends to make uſe of this their ſimplicity, to make them underſtand how much they have been deceived. This is the chief cauſe that hath prevailed upon me to publiſh this little Tract: I may call it little, it is ſo indeed, for it is not to my purpoſe to examin and thoroughly ſift out all the Controverſies of Religion: I muſt needs acknowledge, that I am not ſo well verſed in and acquainted with ſuch matters, which I never underſtood but from the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Schools, as many other Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that have and do write of them. My deſign is only to declare by the motives of my Change of Religion, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> alone is ſufficient to convince any man, and cauſe him to perceive its Abuſes and Errours.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Party ought not to be offended, nor wonder at the hearing any ſcandal caſt upon this Treatiſe or its Author; I intreat them to ſhew me ſo much favour; for they muſt underſtand, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are bound in
<pb facs="tcp:95424:4"/>conſcience, for fear of the guilt of a mortal crime, to ſpeak ill of me. If they did but give the leaſt countenance to a Book that appears with ſuch a Title as this doth, or did but mention with reſpect and honour a perſon that hath done what I have, they would commit a grievous offence againſt the Laws of their Religion, of which they cannot be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, but by thoſe who have obtained the priviledge of giving Abſolution in caſes reſerved to his Holineſs. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides, they believe as they are taught every day by their Preachers, that it is lawful to make uſe of any means to attain unto a good end; that is to ſay, that it is lawful to invent a thouſand lyes and calumnies to ſpoil the credit of a book or of a perſon contrary to their Religion. I muſt not expect a more favourable treatment at their hands, ſeeing that they have been ſo bold for that end to attempt upon the lives of Men, nay of Soveraign Princes, as we may find in the Records of this City, and of other places. But I have no reaſon to be afraid of this kind of perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, I mean of their Tongues, for I may ſay I have lived amongst them without blame, as may be conjectured from the conſiderable Employments which I have had in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> for their Biſhops never admit a perſon into their Cathedrals to preach, unleſs they know him to be of an honeſt and good behaviour: And the Religious of that Order, of which I have made profeſſion, (the <hi>Carmelites</hi>) which doubtleſs is one of the moſt exemplary of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; if theſe had not had a good opinion of me they would never have promoted me to that degree of honour amongst them which I have held, having been three times the Priors Deputy in the ſame Convent, which Office is given to none but to ſuch as are very regular and exemplary in their lives. It is therefore needleſs that any perſon
<pb facs="tcp:95424:5"/>ſhould trouble himſelf with an inquiry for the place from whence I came, and of my carriage while I have remained in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to diſcredit this little Book. I am not afraid in the leaſt of any ſuch thing, I am rather fully perſwaded that there is no man in thoſe Towns where I have made my abode, nor in the Convents where I have dwelt, but will give me the reputation of an honeſt and juſt man, blameleſs in my carriage until now, as much as is poſſible, in caſe the change of my Religion be concealed from them. I think therefore that thou hadſt beſt peruſe this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe with a calm and unprejudiced mind, that thou may'st be better able to judge of the things therein declared, and gather from thence the inſtructions needful to undeceive thy judgment, if thou art yet in the ſame errours as I have been. Thoſe that will read over theſe lines with that good diſpoſition, will approve of my change, and of this publication, and will be conſtrained to confeſs, that there are cauſes and reaſons ſtrong enough to oblige any man to forſake the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi> and embrace the Profeſſion of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="prayer">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95424:5"/>
            <head>The Prayer before Sermon.</head>
            <q>O Lord God, infinite in goodneſs and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, who haſt by the gracious hand of thy divine Providence taken and lead me as <hi>Abram</hi> out of the ſuperſtitious <hi>Ur</hi> of the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> as <hi>Lot</hi> out of the filthy flames of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> as <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of the bondage and tyranny of <hi>Egypt,</hi> as <hi>Joſeph</hi> from his dungeon, as <hi>Daniel</hi> out of the Lions den, and as the blind Man of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> out of that fearful blindneſs which hath ſince my infancy hindred me from the diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very and acknowledgment of thy Sacred Truth! O God, who haſt preſerved me from all perils, and conducted me ſafe out of the hands of enemies with thy powerful and ſtretched out Arm, here I am proſtrate at the foot-ſtool of thy Divine Majeſty, convinced in judgment, with a contrite and an humble ſpirit; here I am in the midſt of thy Elect, of thy Royal Prieſthood, of thy Holy Nation, of thy People purchaſed with thy Blood, in the midſt of Believers; not with an intention to offer up unto thee their prayers, for I am not worthy of ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95424:6"/>holy a Miniſtry, my Tongue is not yet able to ſpeak ſo loud as their ſighs, and my Lips are too much defiled; but I am here to beſeech Thee, O'Searcher of the Heart! to hearken to their vows, and the prayers of their Souls, for the advance of thy Glory, the accompliſhment and preſervation of thy Church, eſpecially for this which worſhips Thee in ſpirit and in truth, in theſe three Kingdoms of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> for the proſperity of the King that Commands here, for his Spouſe Queen <hi>Catherine,</hi> for <hi>James</hi> Duke of <hi>York,</hi> and for all the Royal Family; for the Arch-biſhops, Biſhops, and other Teachers of thy Church, that it may pleaſe Thee to enlighten them with the Spirit of thy Truth, and enflame them with an holy zeal for the Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Souls; for the Lords and others of the Kings Council, for the Magiſtrates and other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habitants of theſe three Kingdoms, that it may pleaſe Thee to ſupply and ſuccour them in all their wants, whether they be ſpiritual or corporal: But more eſpecially we pray Thee for all ſuch as are yet engaged and plunged in errour, take them out of the ſame depths of ſin from whence Thou haſt drawn me; open their eyes whether they will or no, that they may perceive the truth of thy Goſpel; open their hearts by the divine power of thy Holy Spirit, that thy Bleſſed Word may be received as in a good and fruitful field, that it may bring forth an hundred fold! In this occaſion be pleaſed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of my prayers with thy peoples, for I know by experience that Thou alone art able to turn and convince a Soul brought up in errour, and change
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95424:6"/>a heart nouriſhed from its infancy with an abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rency of thy Holy Word! Therefore I pray Thee, or rather we all pray Thee together, to open the eyes of ſo many blind perſons, whom I leave behind me in the regions of darkneſs; and touch with the efficacious finger of thy Holy Spirit, ſo many ſtony hearts that reſiſt the motions and offers of thy Grace with ſo much obſtinacy! Lord, Thou haſt performed in me a bleſſed change, for which I offer up unto Thee my hearty thanks and praiſes, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching Thee to pardon my unworthineſs, and graciouſly to accept of the thanks which thy faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful people here aſſembled do render unto Thee for my ſake! But O merciful God, at this ſame time that I find my ſelf obliged to offer unto Thee my thanks for a favour received from thy hand, I find my ſelf in a neceſſity to beg another favour and mercy of granting unto me the power and ability to declare unto this numerous Congregation the great mercy that Thou haſt ſhewed me by bringing me to my Converſion! I am deſired, O my God! it is but juſt that I ſhould give glory to thy Holy Name; Juſtice and Reaſon require that I ſhould declare thy Goodneſs where iniquity hath ſo long appeared with impudency, that I ſhould employ the members which have been abuſed in warring againſt Thee to diſcover thy wonderful mercy in me; theſe lips, this tongue, and this voice, which hath uttered ſo many lyes and errours againſt the light and ſuggeſtions of thy Holy Spirit; theſe members that have declared ſo many falſhoods, preached up ſo many abuſes, confirmed ſo many
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95424:7"/>blaſphemies, committed and cauſed ſo many ſins to be committed; it is juſt that they ſhould glorifie thy Holy Name! Forgive, O my God! forgive me the ſin of having ſo long detained thy truth in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteouſneſs againſt my conſcience and thy ſecret motions! Grant me the grace that I may this day be able to make an honourable amends, that I may give the ſame teſtimony to thy Bleſſed Truth which I have given to Hereſie; and that I may bring forth fruits ſuitable to my repentance! For this purpoſe, O good God, purifie my unclean lips, touch them with a coal from thine Altar, clenſe this tongue yet ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nomous which hath ſo often conveyed a poiſon into many hearts, inflame it with ſome of thoſe cloven tongues of fire which lighted upon thy Holy Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, and which cauſed them to be no more dumb but eloquent! Change the accent of this voice, which hath been heard in the Pulpits of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion! make it never to be heard any more in vindication of errour, and that it may never accent and pronounce any thing but that which is altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther conformable to thy Word! Theſe are the peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions that I now preſent unto Thee, O good God, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at this time, beſeeching Thee alſo ſo to prepare the ears and hearts of my Hearers, that they may be the better by my diſcourſe, more confirmed and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled in their Faith, and more reſolved in an obedience to Thee! Theſe mercies we beſeech Thee to grant us, O merciful God, by the merits and only mediation of Jeſus Chriſt; in whoſe Bleſſed Name we continue to pray unto Thee, as He Himſelf hath taught us; <hi>Our Father which art in Heaven,</hi> &amp;c.</q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:95424:7"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 5. verſ. 20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>—Where ſin abounded, grace did much more abound.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HEre I am, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> in this Pulpit to acquaint you at preſent with the cauſes of that which you have ſeen me do this morning: I am here to expreſs unto you a repentance ſuitable to the hainouſneſs of my ſins, by a publick abjuration of thoſe grievous errours which I have formerly profeſſed in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> that I might ſhew forth the accompliſhment of this holy Oracle pronounced by St. <hi>Paul, Where ſin abounded, grace did much more abound.</hi> You may be fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, <hi>my Brethren,</hi> that Gods grace hath obliged and conſtrained me to what I have done, for my Change of Religion proceeds not from the uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtancy of my mind; I have done nothing ſuddenly, I have been ſeven years in a continual deliberation, ſtruggling with my ſelf, convinced in my judgment, but could never reſolve until now. You muſt not therefore look upon my alteration as the effect of ſome calamity, or the conſequence of an unworthy behaviour, or a diſgrace: I never wanted bread, I have always had too much at command, and have
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95424:8"/>ever met with more happineſs in my undertakings than I could expect. Neither is this Change the product of any miſcarriage; no, bleſſed be God, I am not aſhamed of any thing that I have done, thoſe Honourable Perſons unto whom I have been recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in this place may bear witneſs from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of ſuch as are worthy of credit. The greateſt crime that I have committed is that which I have been guilty of this day, by forſaking a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitious Religion and embracing a purer, by leaving the broad road to Hell and turning into that of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven. God out of his infinite goodneſs and mercy hath obliged me to it, notwithſtanding all the natural perſwaſions of worldly intereſt; for I have left the aſſurance of a ſufficient proviſion for my mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, to embarque my ſelf and rely wholly upon Gods good providence. I have cauſed my beſt friends to become my moſt deadly enemies, I have made of my parents and relations my perſecutors and ſworn adverſaries, I have left forever a Country where I enjoyed as much worldly happineſs as was poſſible, to come to live and dye in another, where I have no other expectation nor means to advance my ſelf but only from your kindneſs and favour. God knows how ſtrong theſe reaſons have been to detain me ſo long, and what difficulty I have had to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand my ſelf to a final reſolution, but at laſt grace hath overcome; God hath had in me more power than the world and humane reaſon, and the hopes of my ſalvation more than the advantages of this life. That I might declare this unto you, I have now the liberty to appear in this Pulpit, I ſhall therefore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95424:8"/>do it as briefly as I am able, I ſhall give you an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of ſome of thoſe diſputes which I have main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in my mind, before I could reſolve to do what I have at laſt done: I ſhall therefore begin to declare the reaſons that have kept me ſo long in the profeſſion of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion, and that as far as I am able to judge do detain the reſt of its Profeſſors: I ſhall afterwards diſcover to you the reaſons that have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed the firſt groundleſs reaſons, and that have cauſed me to forſake the <hi>Romiſh Religion</hi> and embrace the <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> to renounce <hi>errour</hi> for <hi>faith, hereſie</hi> and <hi>idolatry</hi> for the <hi>truth,</hi> the babyloniſh <hi>Rome</hi> for the celeſtial <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> my <hi>Country</hi> for <hi>Haven,</hi> and <hi>all</hi> for my <hi>God.</hi> By this Diſcourſe you ſhall perceive the greatneſs of Gods mercy towards me, in that he hath been pleaſed of a ſtone to raiſe up a ſon to <hi>Abraham,</hi> and hath cauſed his grace to abound where ſin aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>THE FIRST PART.</head>
               <p>THe firſt and chief cauſe which hath ſo long detai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned me in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is, that venerable Antiquity which is aſcribed to her alone: I did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times conſider her gray hairs, her pretended Founder the Apoſtle St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who as it is ſaid governed her during the ſpace of five and twenty years: I did ſometimes look upon her Sovereign Authority, which ſhe ſaith Chriſt himſelf gave unto her in the perſon of that Apoſtle, which ſince hath continued ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively in all the Popes who have commanded in that See: This Succeſſion of the Popes and Biſhops
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95424:9"/>of <hi>Rome</hi> hath never been violated nor interrupted, as they pretend, but they have immediately ſucceeded to one another; the like is not to be ſeen in any other Church. Beſides, I did ſometimes view a long Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talogue of Martyrs and other Saints, who are ſaid to have lived in an obedience to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and to be dead in the profeſſion of that Faith which is there now, and hath been always taught, as is pretended. I did examin all theſe plauſible Titles, theſe glorious Attributes, and her divine Preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, as I found them recorded in the Books and Schools of that Church, which could not but oblige me to an high eſteem of her excellency, and to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der how men could be ſo blind and irrational as to deny her to be the only true Catholick and Apoſtolick Church. In this manner, my Brethren, I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued about the ſpace of ſix or ſeven years, ſeriouſly conſidering theſe advantages that were given to this Church: At laſt I took that liberty which is not granted to any of that profeſſion, and that is, to open my eyes and examin more narrowly from whence proceeded theſe magnificent and glorious Attributes, and what reaſons <hi>Rome</hi> hath to claim them to her ſelf alone: For that purpoſe I peruſed the Holy Scriptures, and its moſt ancient Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, as the moſt worthy of credit, and by them I was conſtrained to alter my judgment, and to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain perſwaſions contrary to that received from my Forefathers, from my Maſters, and from the Reading of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Divines.</p>
               <p>I have found that Antiquity, in which <hi>Rome</hi> boaſts ſo much, diſcovers her ſhame and diſgrace, as the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95424:9"/>Antiquity of a Noble Family is a reproach to a dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerated Son. I have found that the Authority which ſhe claims hath no other foundation nor beginning, but the pride and tyranny of ſuch Popes as have ſucceeded <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great, for neither he nor any of his Predeceſſors have ever thought it lawful for them to challenge or pretend to an univerſal Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion or Authority in the Church. I have found this Succeſſion, which is ſaid to be without interruption, to be an abyſs, where the moſt learned Hiſtorians loſe themſelves; they can find no ſure footing, ſo that they themſelves are forced to confeſs, that they flote upon the waves of a Sea ſubject to calms and tempeſts, to ebbing and flowing, if I may make uſe of their own expreſſions. Sometimes they ſee this Ship of St. <hi>Peter</hi> without Helm or Pilot, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed with the billows, without hope of a reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very or expectation of ſalvation for ſuch as are there imbarqued. I have found that the Holineſs where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with this Church was adorned under the Conduct of its ancient Biſhops, is at preſent much degenera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, an univerſal corruption hath ſpread it ſelf into all the Members of this politick Body; ſo that where grace did formerly abound, there at preſent ſin and hereſie abound, to the ſhame and diſgrace of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity. This I have found, as ſoon as I could open my eyes to take notice of ſuch matters without pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice or partiality, which we muſt baniſh from us if we will give a true judgment: This I have learned in the ſtudy of Holy Scripture, in the reading of the ancient Fathers of the Church, and from the Records of Antiquity, without the aſſiſtance of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95424:10"/>
                  <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Books, or any information from Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters.</p>
               <p>§. Antiquity hath always had a Command over the minds and judgments of men: We look commonly with a great deal of reverence and reſpect upon a head which time hath loaden with gray hairs, and which diſcovers the number of its years by the many wrinkles of its face; we ſee many times the ruins of an old Dwelling, encompaſſed about with a few rotten Oaks, is more looked upon than the nobleſt Palaces, reared up according to the neweſt and moſt regular form of Art; a Braſs Medal ſhall be more eſteemed than ten others of a more precious Metal, if it can but ſhew forth the Image and Name of ſome ancient Monarch, or of a Conquerour of former Ages. This reſpect, which Nature and Cuſtome diſcover for things of a long continuance, is not diſagreeable to the directions of Moral and of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Policy: We are to have more eſteem for a State that hath ſubſiſted a thouſand years, than for another that hath continued but one or two hundred; and we are adviſed to have moſt regard for that Religion which can produce the ancienteſt Records, and prove its eſtabliſhment to be the firſt.</p>
               <p>This hath always been my judgment. As there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I did look upon the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> as the moſt ancient, as that which had been founded by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle St. <hi>Peter,</hi> as the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> would perſwade us, I have for a long while entertained the greateſt eſteem
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95424:10"/>for her, and judged ſuch as were not agreeable to her Principles to be but haſty productions of Nature, in compariſon of an ancient Tree, or as Baſtards in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of the Child well born. I did wonder how men could harbour any other thoughts. My Mind being thus filled with partiality for my ancient Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, I could not imagin how any man of wit and ability, without being grievouſly blinded, could embrace any other. I did oft-times argue with my ſelf in this manner: Is it poſſible, that there ſhould be ſome men ſo ſilly and ridiculous, to prefer a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion which we have ſeen in its Cradle, to another which hath continued ſixteen hundred years; a Church formed by the wit of <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Beza,</hi> and ſome others, to that which Chriſt and His Holy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles have eſtabliſhed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Thus it is, ſaith <hi>Lactan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> in his Book of the <hi>Riſe of Errour, l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 7. Thus Antiquity commands the judgments of men: <hi>Its authority is ſo great, that we look upon it as a crime to inquire into the qualities of that which is ancient, and to queſtion its rights; credit is given to it at the firſt ſight, as to a moſt known truth. In the ſame manner</hi> (ſaith that Author, <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8.) <hi>ſome imprudently neglect the advice of wiſdom, approving without any examination the inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of their forefathers, ſuffering themſelves to be lead as beaſts whitherſoever others pleaſe, and not whither they ſhould go. In this manner they are deceived, and are willing to be ſo, by taking for the rule of their faith the belief of their forefathers, out of a ſtrong conceit, that they cannot be wiſer than they were before, becauſe they have ſucceeded them, and that it is not probable that they were deceived, ſeeing that they have preceded them and are named their anceſtors.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:95424:11"/>Theſe words of this wiſe man, and ſome paſſages of others, made me think, that it was not ſo great a crime as is declared in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min the Antiquity of the Religion of our Forefathers, and to conſider from whence it proceeds, whither it tends, what it hath been, what it ſhould be, what are its Priviledges, Duties, Doctrine, Laws, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct; if that which is profeſſed to day be the ſame as that of yeſterday, that of this age be like to that of the firſt times, or whether it be not differing, or a ſtrange Baſtard put into the room of the true Child; whether it hath not robb'd the lawful Heireſs of her Titles of Honour, uſurped her Rights by counterfeit Letters, ſeiſed upon her Demeſnes, driven her from her Inheritance; baniſhed her out of her Dominion by a diſguiſe under the moſt beautiful habits; and whether by this means the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church hath not ſeated her ſelf in the ſeat of the lawful, to procure unto her ſelf a greater eſteem amongſt men, who have ſo much reſpect for things that appear with a grave and ancient countenance.</p>
               <p>I have ſeriouſly examined theſe things, I have ſought for the Rights and Titles of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> amongſt its pretended Anceſtors, Chriſt, St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who have been, ſaith ſhe, my Founders and Apoſtles. I have read over the Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges that they aſcribe to her, and the Duties that they require from her, that which ſhe hath received from them, and that which they command her to have, the language which they teach her, and the Laws that they have given her, and how they beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved themſelves that ſucceeded immediately after her
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95424:11"/>firſt Founders. When I had thus compared the one with the other, the preſent <hi>Rome</hi> with the ancient, the World that is now with that which was, the Children with the Father, that which is believed and preached at preſent with that which was believed and preached heretofore, that which was practiſed and that which is now done, that which is ſeen with that which was anciently; I have found, after a ſerious examination of all theſe things, that there can be nothing more contrary than theſe two things, the ancient Chriſtian <hi>Rome</hi> and that which appears now, the Church then with the modern, the Faith and Chriſtian Religion under the Popes Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment with that Faith and Religion which the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> firſt embraced, and profeſſed a long whiles under the Teachers and Biſhops which the Apoſtles left them. Let any man read over the Goſpel and the Records of the Primitive Chriſtians, ſince the time of the Apoſtles until the fourth or fifth Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turies, to ſeek what Church Jeſus Chriſt eſtabliſhed upon the unmoveable foundation of His Word and Merits; let him take notice of that which St. <hi>Luke</hi> deſcribes better with his Pen than with his skilful Pencil, of that which all the approved Writers of the Eccleſiaſtical Affairs immediately ſucceeding do repreſent unto us, which profeſſed no other belief but in Jeſus Chriſt, which had rejected an Angel from Heaven, if he had preached any other Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine but that which is contained in the Holy Goſpel, and in the other Books of Sacred Scripture. This Church acknowledged no other but Chriſt, looked upon ſuch as named themſelves of <hi>Apollo</hi>'s Party,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95424:12"/>of <hi>Peter</hi>'s or <hi>Paul</hi>'s, as ſo many Sectaries, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of no other Judge of Controverſies and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour but Jeſus Chriſt. Call but to mind all that you have ever read or heard of this Church, ſince its beginning, until the time of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi>'s uſurpation of the Sovereign Power, under the name of <hi>Pope,</hi> and compare that Church of <hi>Rome</hi> with this in our days, examine the Tenents, Maxims, Laws, Behaviour, and Cuſtoms of both, and you will be forced to confeſs, that they are not the ſame, but two Churches, as much differing the one from the other as the day from the night. We muſt not therefore mention the Antiquity of this Church, but as of a languiſhing and decayed Body we may ſay ſhe is ancient, in the ſame manner as we ſay of women that ſhamefully yield themſelves to pleaſure in their old age, whilſt they were young, chaſt, and beautiful, they were worthily eſteemed and admired of every one, but ſince age and lechery, time and debauchery, ſeiſes upon them, they become ſo ſtrangely altered, that they ſeem not to be the ſame perſons. We muſt look upon the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> in this manner: She is no longer that beautiful Won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that raviſhing Spouſe, whoſe Picture <hi>Solomon</hi> labours to draw in <hi>chap.</hi> 4. of the <hi>Canticles;</hi> but an old Whore, the Mother of fornications and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of the earth, mentioned by St. <hi>John, Revel. chap.</hi> 17. She is old I confeſs, like unto thoſe old Palaces, which time and want of repair have brought to ruin. I may expreſs this by another reſemblance: She is ancient, as are the old Bodies infected with Leproſie, and abounding with vicious humours,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95424:12"/>which putrefie the older they grow, and corrupt the more with age, the continuance of the diſeaſe ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo changed their conſtitution, that they are not to be known by the former idea's of their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons. In this manner the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church may be ſaid to be ancient: Antiquity doth but diſcover her ſhame, reveal her Apoſtacy, and declare her grievous Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions. Let us ſay ſomething more to the purpoſe.</p>
               <p>Men are known by their ſpeech, the home-born Inhabitants of a Country are diſtinguiſhable from ſtrangers by their language and pronunciation. I deſire no more, to ſhew that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not the true Church of Chriſt, and that the preſent Church is not the ſame as that which was firſt eſtabliſhed: Liſten to the language of both, and you ſhall find a vaſt difference; hearken to the Popes language and to that of Jeſus Chriſt, to what the one commands and the other forbids, to what the firſt affirms and the latter denies, to what Chriſt with his Apoſtles preach and the Pope with his Doctors declare and publiſh. We need but read the Holy Goſpel and the Decretals of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Scripture and the Canons of the Council of <hi>Trent,</hi> the Books of the ancient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and the Belief of the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> and of modern Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors; to underſtand, that the Church which ſtiles her ſelf <hi>Chriſtian, Catholick, Apoſtolick,</hi> and <hi>Roman,</hi> is nothing of all that, and deſerves none of thoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Titles, for ſhe is neither <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> nor <hi>Catholick,</hi> nor <hi>Apoſtolick,</hi> nor <hi>Roman,</hi> if we take the <hi>Roman</hi> Church for what ſhe was anciently. She cannot be properly named <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> becauſe ſhe acknowledgeth another Lord and Superiour beſides Jeſus Chriſt, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95424:13"/>denies Him to be the only Saviour of Men, aſcribing this honour to the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and others, by ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that ſhe may and doth ſave many by her interce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for them, that the Pope is able to do the like by pardoning their ſins and granting unto them his Indulgences, and that they themſelves may contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to their own ſalvation by their good works, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> She is not <hi>Catholick,</hi> in that ſenſe which the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> give to this word, becauſe ſhe preaches a Doctrine not agreeable to that which God hath revealed to us by His Son and Miniſters, and prefers her own Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions before the Oracles of the Holy Scripture, becauſe ſhe invents many ſuperſtitious Laws which occaſion grievous ſins. She is not <hi>Roman,</hi> like unto that Church which was anciently ſo called, for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that primitive Church, as we ſhall further take notice, never did claim an univerſal Dominion, for ſhe did acknowledge the Churches of <hi>Antioch, Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria,</hi> and of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and others, to be her equals in all reſpects; therefore her Biſhops never believed themſelves to be their ſuperiours, but their brethren and companions. The Chriſtians of thoſe days un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood nothing of Indulgences, of Fraternities, of Holy-water, of Conſecrated Crums, of Relicks and Repoſitories, of Medals and Beads, and other ſuch like Baubles, in which the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> placeth the Holineſs of Chriſtianity. They knew nothing of Holy Bread, kept in little Tabernacles, to be there worſhipped; they never had in their Churches Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, like to thoſe of <hi>Rome,</hi> as may appear by the words of <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> who lived in the fourth Century, and writ to <hi>John</hi> the Patriarch of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:95424:13"/>which St. <hi>Jerome</hi> hath tranſlated into <hi>Latin,</hi> and therefore declares the Judgment of thoſe two Eminent Perſons. In this Epiſtle he ſaith, that when he went into a Church, ſituate in a Country Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lage, he perceived upon the door a veil where there was an Image to be ſeen, therefore he cauſed it to be taken down, and to be torn in pieces; for, ſaith he, by this means men may introduce Idolatry a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt Chriſtians. By this paſſage we may under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that the Worſhip of Images was a ſtrange thing in that Age, as other Hiſtorians, and after them <hi>Baronius,</hi> are forced to confeſs. Chriſtians of thoſe days did rather chuſe to be burned alive and tormented, than to ſuffer the leaſt grain of Incenſe to fall from their hands into that fire, which was intended to burn it in honour of an Image or Idol, which they were required to worſhip. Thoſe wiſe and couragious Chriſtians did chuſe rather to behold their own Arms and Members conſume in a fire, and endure the moſt ſenſible pains and tortures, than to behold the Smoak of Incenſe, fallen from their hands, mount up to the noſe of a ſenſeleſs Idol. They did rather chuſe to expoſe themſelves to the fury of the fires, and of drawn ſwords, and undergo the torments of the wheels, of the wild beaſts, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> than to bow their knees before a graven Image, and yield unto it the leaſt reſpect. O <hi>Romans</hi> of our days! if any of the ancient Chriſtians could but riſe out of their graves, to come amongſt you into your Churches on ſome Feſtival day, what would they ſay or think, when they ſhould ſee the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Ezekiel</hi>'s Prophecy, <hi>chap.</hi> 8. ſo many abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95424:14"/>in the midſt of God's Sanctuary, the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip due to God alone paid to dumb Pictures which ſtand about the walls of your Temples? when they ſhould ſee that your Chriſtian Devotion conſiſts chiefly in ſuch apiſh tricks, in the kiſſing of Altars, in cringings, ſtretching out of your arms, and ſigns of the Croſs often made, ſometimes three or five times in kneeling before an Image, with hands lifted up, in offering to it frankincenſe, in numbring a few beads, in caſting holy water upon the bones of the deceaſed, in burning a wax candle, put out and lighted again as many times as you have things to deſire from a Saint, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> How many tears would theſe ancient Catholick <hi>Roman</hi> Chriſtians ſhed, when they ſhould ſee this Church practiſing ſuch fooliſh things, ſo much contrary to the Truth of Chriſtian Religion? How many ſighs, groans, and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations ſhould we hear from their pious Souls? <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remiah</hi> never uttered ſo many over the Ruins of <hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi> O <hi>Rome! Rome!</hi> would they ſay, what change is this? what are theſe impertinencies? what won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful <hi>metamorphoſis?</hi> Heretofore the Truth did com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand in thee over Errour, the Laws of God over the Inventions of men, the Precepts of the Goſpel over the Traditions of the people, and true Piety over Superſtition, and God's Worſhip was chiefly regarded; but now we ſee the contrary. Therefore the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> which is now, is not the ſame as that Chriſtian Church of <hi>Rome</hi> firſt eſtabliſhed there, but a ſhadow of it, which hath nothing of its likeneſs. I would deſire the <hi>Papiſts</hi> never to boaſt of the Age and Antiquity of their Church, they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95424:14"/>have no reaſon to glory, in that <hi>Rome</hi> was anciently one of the moſt famous Churches of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> for it is not like what it was heretofore. <hi>Miſerum iſtud verbum fuiſſe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Seneca.</hi> It is but a ſad com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, and a bad cauſe of glory, to ſay <hi>we have been,</hi> if we cannot ſay alſo we are yet. This the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſhould endeavour to make good unto us. They ought to ſhew us by their Doctrine and Works, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> at preſent is the ſame as it was of old, which cannot be done but by a refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of all the abuſes, and a reducement to the firſt eſtate; whilſt they continue as they are, they ſhall never diſcover what their firſt fathers have been. The moſt learned of all their Doctors, who have undertaken to ſhew their conformity with the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſeem to be much perplex'd in the proving of this matter, very weak in their ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments, and ſo contrary to one another, that we need but their own Books to find out the falſhood of their Doctrine. This every one may take notice, that will peruſe them without partiality. I might here name an hundred paſſages out of their Books to prove the truth of what I ſay, but I think I have ſaid enough to make the <hi>Papiſts</hi> apply unto themſelves <hi>Tertullians</hi> reproach, directed to the Heathens, <hi>Apol. adv. Gent. cap. 6. Tell me, where is your Religion? where is that reſpect that ye owe to your forefathers? you are not like to them in your habits, in your manner of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, in your cuſtoms, opinions, and in your language: You praiſe antiquity, but every day you admit new inventions: You differ much from the worthy inſtitutions of your pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors: You declare by your behaviour, that you retain
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95424:15"/>nothing of thoſe things that deſerve to be retained, but obſerve that which deſerves it not.</hi> This is a true repreſentation of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§ In the next place, that Sovereign Authority which this Church claims did ſeem to me to be very well grounded, when I did conſider that which Jeſus Chriſt ſaith to St. <hi>Peter</hi> in many occaſions, eſpecially in that where He tells him, immediately after the Confeſſion of his Faith, <hi>Thou art</hi> Peter, <hi>and upon this Rock I will build my Church, and the gates of hell ſhall not prevail againſt it; I will give unto thee the keys of the kingdom of heaven, whatſoever thou ſhalt bind on earth ſhall be bound in heaven, and whatſoever thou ſhalt looſe in earth ſhall be looſed in heaven: Matth.</hi> 16. By theſe words, Chriſt ſeems to give unto him and his Succeſſors a full power, and more than to the reſt. There are other paſſages of Holy Scripture that make for the ſame purpoſe, and St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Interpreters, ſeem to favour this opinion, and Reaſon it ſelf ſeems to teach us the neceſſity of a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Head over Chriſt's Church on earth, anſwerable to its eſtate. In this manner I did argue with my Comrades, having been inſtructed in the Schools of <hi>Thomas Aquinas, Suarez,</hi> and others, that gather from thence many reaſons to prove the Pope's Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Sovereignty. But when I had a little better examined theſe paſſages, peruſed the Writings of the Fathers, to underſtand their judgment of this matter, I have found that there is nothing more
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95424:15"/>falſe than the Doctrines of the Popiſh Schools in this occaſion; for Chriſt's words to St. <hi>Peter</hi> were not ſaid to him alone, as may appear if we look into the Goſpel, for Jeſus Chriſt asked not only <hi>Peter,</hi> but all His Diſciples, and <hi>Peter</hi> anſwers not only in his own name, but alſo in that of the reſt of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, <hi>in perſona omnium Apoſtolorum</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and the other ancient Interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters; which words the <hi>Papiſts</hi> have inſerted into their <hi>Breviarum,</hi> or Rubrick, ſpeaking of this paſſage: When therefore the Son of God returns unto St. <hi>Peter,</hi> as a reward of his confeſſion, the power of binding and looſing, and the keys of heaven, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> it is not to him alone that He ſpeaks and grants all theſe priviledges, but to the reſt, in whoſe name St. <hi>Peter</hi> did anſwer, therefore a few days after He repeated unto them the ſame thing, and confirm'd the ſame priviledge to all the reſt of His Apoſtles, <hi>Whatſoever ye ſhall bind on earth ſhall be bound in heaven,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. <hi>verſ.</hi> 18. He addreſſeth Himſelf to them all, and not to one alone: And if after His Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, Chriſt ſpeaks to St. <hi>Peter</hi> only, <hi>Feed my ſheep;</hi> this was as St. <hi>Cyril,</hi> and other wiſe Interpreters have taken notice, with an intent to confirm and re-admit him into the office of an Apoſtle, which he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced by his Apoſtacy from Chriſt. He had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied his Maſter thrice, therefore the Son of God propoſes this queſtion, <hi>Loveſt thou me?</hi> three times. All this is noted in the <hi>Roman</hi> Rubrick. <hi>Thrice</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Cyril, lib.</hi> 12. <hi>chap.</hi> 64.) <hi>He commands him to feed His ſheep, to renew unto him the dignity, and confirm him in the office of an Apoſtle, for fear that the denial of his
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95424:16"/>Lord, which he had been guilty of through the weakneſs of the fleſh, ſhould ſeem to have caſhier'd him.</hi> For it is to contradict what Jeſus Chriſt ſaid to all His A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, when He appointed them to preach the Goſpel to Mankind, to teach and baptize, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to ſay that none but St. <hi>Peter</hi> had this power granted to him.</p>
               <p>But a great many paſſages of Holy Scripture do expreſly contradict this Doctrine: <hi>You have but one Maſter, but one Father, which is in heaven,</hi> ſaith Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Matth.</hi> 23. <hi>verſ.</hi> 8. <hi>I am the good Shepherd, I know my Sheep, and lay down my life for them:</hi> He ſaith not, I am an hired Shepherd, but the true Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, <hi>John</hi> 11. As there is but one Flock, there can be but one Shepherd; now who is this Shepherd, Chriſt or the Pope? <hi>My Father hath given me all power, in heaven and in earth, Matth.</hi> 28. <hi>I have power to pardon ſins on earth, Mark</hi> 2.10. <hi>God hath committed all judgment unto me,</hi> and power to execute judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>John</hi> 5. How can theſe paſſages agree with the Popes Sovereign Authority? Is it not a grievous affront offered to Jeſus Chriſt, to ſet this Divine Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour aſide, as <hi>Bellarmin</hi> doth, <hi>ſecluſo Chriſto,</hi> to help up the Pope to his Throne, and inveſt him into his uſurped Sovereignty? If we are to acknowledge but one <hi>Shepherd,</hi> but one <hi>Maſter,</hi> but one <hi>Lord,</hi> but one only <hi>Heir</hi> of the Fathers Power and Authority, ſhall we not rob Chriſt of theſe His Divine Prerogatives, if we ſhould offer to beſtow them upon the Pope?</p>
               <p>I am not ignorant of all the diſtinctions made uſe of in this occaſion, to juſtifie the Pope from this Uſurpation, but they are but philoſophical and aiery diſtinctions, of the ſame nature as are commonly
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95424:16"/>invented by the wit of man, to juſtifie <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> from his Belief and Doctrine of the Worlds Eternity; <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> and others, from their ſaying that the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> was conceived in ſin; <hi>Tertullian, Origen,</hi> St. <hi>Bernard,</hi> and others, from teaching that the Souls of Saints are not admitted to the Viſion of God before the day of Judgment. They are ſuch like diſtinctions as the <hi>Pirrhenians</hi> invented, to prove that white was black, that a hat was the ſame as a ſlipper, and an Ape like a Lion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All theſe arguments and diſtinctions might be well reſented from the mouth of <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> of <hi>Plato, Pythagoras,</hi> or from a <hi>Carteſian</hi> Philoſopher, but not from a Catholick Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, who ought not to mind what he might ſay, but what he ſhould believe in conſcience; not what he can maintain, but what he is bound to embrace. When an Article of our Faith is concerned, ſuch a one muſt ſet aſide his diſputing humour, and the quirks and tricks of Logick, taught him in the Schools, to make a plain and ſincere profeſſion of the Truth. For my part, I think it is the beſt, to declare ingenuouſly, that there can be no ſolid reaſon found out, to authorize our aſcribing to a man that which belongs to Jeſus Chriſt alone by his own words. No man can juſtly condemn me, for having denied to the Pope, that which I read in the Goſpel to be Chriſts Prerogative only: <hi>It is not poſſible,</hi> faith an ancient Father, <hi>to give too much to God;</hi> eſpecially when man enters into competition with Him.</p>
               <p>But liſten, I pray, to what the Apoſtles and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive Fathers ſay upon this Article: <hi>There is one ſovereign or great Shepherd of our Souls,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Peter,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95424:17"/>Ep.</hi> 1. <hi>chap. 5. with whom, when He ſhall appear, we ſhall appear alſo with Him in glory; ſuch as feed the flock of Chriſt committed to their charge, taking the overſight thereof, not by conſtraint, but willingly, not for filthy lucre, but of a ready mind, neither as being lords over Gods heritage, but,</hi> &amp;c. Doth St. <hi>Peter</hi> eſtabliſh here the Popes Monarchy? doth not he rather undermine the foundation of it? <hi>No man,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, can lay another foundation but that which is already laid, Jeſus Chriſt. There is one Lawgiver. Who art thou,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>James, that judgeſt another? He hath the Keys of</hi> David, <hi>that opens and none can ſhut, that ſhuts and no man can open, Revel.</hi> 3. How doth this agree with that which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> would perſwade us of St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and of the Pope? Ought we not to gather from theſe paſſages, Doctrines contrary to their belief? <hi>No man can lay another foundation,</hi> &amp;c. They are therefore much deceived, that affirm, that St. <hi>Peter</hi> is the foundation of the Chriſtian Church, and that the Pope is the head. There is but one Lawgiver, the Pope therefore hath no authority to command and appoint Laws: He is to be looked upon as a Deceiver, when he would perſwade us, that they are all out of the Church, that will not acknowledge his power. Jeſus Chriſt hath the Key of Heaven, He opens and no man can ſhut, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I muſt therefore ſeek an entrance from Him, if He opens me the door, I ſhall be admitted, maugre the Pope, his Prieſts and Excommunications; if He ſhuts it to me, the Pope hath no Abſolution nor Indulgence of a ſufficient efficacy and power to open it. All the primitive Doctors confirm this Doctrine, they aſcribe to Jeſus
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95424:17"/>Chriſt only, that which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> aſcribe to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> and to the Pope, whom they have made his Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor. <hi>When Jeſus Chriſt</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Chryſoſtome, Tom.</hi> 3. <hi>Ser. de pent.) hath ſaid, upon this Rock I will build my Church, He did not ſay upon</hi> Peter, <hi>for He hath not built His Church upon a man, but upon this Faith. What means</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auſtin, Tract.</hi> 10. <hi>in Epiſt. Joan.) what means He by theſe words, upon this Rock I will build my Church? He means upon this Faith, becauſe he had ſaid, Thou art Chriſt the Son of the living God.</hi> St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Hilary, Theophylact,</hi> and many others, affirm the ſame thing. <hi>Optat. Millevitanus</hi> ſpeaking of Pope <hi>Siricius,</hi> he doth not call him <hi>Maſter</hi> or <hi>Holy Father, &amp;c.</hi> but <hi>Noſter Socius,</hi> our Companion, <hi>Contra Parmen. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>Art thou bordering upon</hi> Achaia (ſaith <hi>Tertullian, de Praet. cap.</hi> 36.) <hi>thou art near to</hi> Corinth, <hi>if thou art joyning to</hi> Macedonia <hi>thou haſt</hi> Philippi Theſſalonica, <hi>if thou canſt go over into</hi> Aſia <hi>thou ſhalt find</hi> Epheſus, <hi>and if thou neighboureſt upon</hi> Italy <hi>thou art not far from</hi> Rome, <hi>where we have authority.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus the Primitive Fathers diſcourſe unto us of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> They never aſcribed unto her any more power or priviledge, than to all the other Churches. Let any man therefore judge, what im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudency and preſumption the Popes are guilty of, in that they claim a Sovereign Power, not only over Spiritual Affairs, but alſo over the temporal, in all Chriſtian Kingdoms. How blind, or rather how mali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious, muſt the Popiſh Divines be, to employ all their learning and skill in maintaining of this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine? I am perſwaded, that there are but few that commit this ſin out of ignorance. Do you judge if
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95424:18"/>it be not a grievous blaſphemy, to extol the Pope as thoſe Doctors do, and to appropriate unto him theſe Titles and Praiſes given him by ſome Councils; for example, that which Pope <hi>Nicholas II.</hi> ſaid of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Can. omnes diſt.</hi> 22. <hi>That be was inveſted with the Empire of Heaven and Earth.</hi> And <hi>Martin V.</hi> named himſelf, <hi>The Light of the World, and the Father of Kings,</hi> &amp;c. The modeſteſt of them all have ſuffered themſelves to be called, without renting their gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> once did in a like occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, <hi>The King of Kings, the Sovereign of the World, the Judge of all Controverſies, from whoſe Sentence there is no appeal to God's Tribunal, for it were to appeal from one to the ſame Being, for God's Authority and that of the Popes is but the ſame;</hi> as if the Father, the Son, the Holy Ghoſt, and the Pope, were but one God. They name him alſo, <hi>the Lamb of God who taketh away the ſins of the world, God's Majeſty on earth, the Brightneſs of God's Preſence, the Bridegroom of the Chriſtian Church, the Lion of the Tribe of</hi> Juda, <hi>God's Vicegerent, the Holy of Holies, Infallible, Almighty,</hi> &amp;c. The Popes have claimed theſe and many other Titles, which I am ready to ſhew, not only in the Writings of the <hi>Roman</hi> Doctors, but alſo in their Rubricks, if any man ſhall queſtion what I now ſay. They have claimed them both by word and deed, requiring the Kings themſelves to kiſs their ſlippers, and with their feet they have caſt down the Crowns of Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours from their heads, as Pope <hi>Celeſtin</hi> treated <hi>Henry</hi> the Sixth: They have trampled them under their feet, as <hi>Alexander</hi> did the Crown of <hi>Frederick Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baroſſa.</hi> What may be more ſaid of Jeſus Chriſt, to
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95424:18"/>put a difference between him and the Pope? Here is the fulfilling of all the Impieties which St. <hi>Paul</hi> did foretell, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 3. <hi>The man of ſin ſhall be revealed, the ſon of perdition, who oppoſeth and exalteth himſelf above all that is called God, on that is worſhipped, ſo that he as God ſitteth in the Temple of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§ The pretended Succeſſion of the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops, ſo much ſpoken of in their Writings, and in the Pulpits of that Church, did ſeem to me to be very well grounded in Holy Scripture; and by the continued Catalogue of all the Popes, which the modern Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh Authors have gathered from the ancient Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, I did judge, that this was but the conſequence of Chriſt's promiſe to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> when He told him, <hi>that his faith ſhould never fail,</hi> and <hi>that the gates of hell ſhould never prevail againſt his Church.</hi> I was perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that this was plainly to be ſeen in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> that above ſixteen hundred years no Schiſm hath been ſo great, as to hinder the Popes to ſucceed one after another. There is no place in the world, where ſo long and noble a Catalogue is to be ſeen, and a Succeſſion of ſo many lawful Biſhops.</p>
               <p>But ſince I have curiouſly examined the Truth, ſince I have look'd into the Hiſtories to find out this continued Succeſſion of <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops for ſo many years, I have found the Writers ſo perplex'd upon this Subject, nay the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves are ſo obſcure and ambiguous, that we may juſtly ſay, that the moſt part of them ſpeak they know not what, for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:95424:19"/>moſt of them are guilty of contradiction; for how can they agree this continued Succeſſion without interruption, with what <hi>Onuphrius</hi> ſaith in his <hi>Chro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicle,</hi> where he mentions no leſs than ſix and twenty Schiſms in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> the twentieth laſted forty years, and the twenty ſixth continued ſince <hi>Urbanus VI.</hi> until the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> as <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brard</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chron. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>an.</hi> 1378. the one and twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth laſted ſix and thirty years, as the ſame Author affirms; during all this time the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> had two Popes, that did excommunicate one another, <hi>Ann.</hi> 1389? How can we agree this Succeſſion with what <hi>Baronius</hi> ſaith? for he is forced to acknowledge it, after ſo many Hiſtorians, that at <hi>Rome</hi> there have been no leſs than three Popes together, whom he names <hi>tricipitem beſtiam portis inferis emergentem, tom.</hi> 11. and <hi>ann.</hi> 1044. <hi>ſect.</hi> 5. a beaſt with three heads aſcending out of the bottomleſs pit.</p>
               <p>All three ſaith <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> namely, <hi>Gregory XIII. Benedictus XIII.</hi> and <hi>John XXIII.</hi> had the ſame ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent right to the Popes Miter, <hi>de pontif. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 14. How can we alſo agree this Doctrine with <hi>Baronius, an.</hi> 912. <hi>ſect.</hi> 8? He ſaith, <hi>That the Clergy were not admitted to the Election, that the Canons were not obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and all ancient Cuſtoms of chuſing Popes ſet aſide: what Cardinals think ye</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that theſe Monſters did create? for according to the uſual courſe of nature every thing begets its likeneſs,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Lechery</hi> (ſaith <hi>Platin. in vita</hi> Benedicti) <hi>brought forth theſe Monſters, theſe Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digies, who by ambition and gifts have intruded them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in, and not lawfully enjoyed St.</hi> Peter's <hi>Chair.</hi> See what the Hiſtorians of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> have
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95424:19"/>been forced to acknowledge, although they have en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to palliate its imperfections, and hide them from the knowledge of the world. How can any have the impudency to maintain, that the Faith of this Church hath never failed? that the gates of hell could never prevail againſt it? and that there was never any diſcontinuance in the ſucceſſion of its Biſhops, <hi>&amp;c?</hi> Yet this is impudently affirmed, with allowance, in the Schools of the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> This Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine I have alſo heretofore defended in <hi>Theſes,</hi> which I publiſhed amongſt them: That although the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops hath paſſed almoſt at every time by bribes, fraud, violence, murder, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath been frequently, and for a long while, divided into Sects and Facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that much diſorder hath happened in it, nevertheleſs we ought to believe and affirm, that the Holy Ghoſt did govern theſe Elections, and that they were by Gods appointment, and that the Faith of this Church hath never failed; becauſe I did ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe there hath always been a wonderful agreement between all its Members, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Let any man judge, if ever <hi>Arius, Pelagius, Marcion,</hi> or any other Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tick, did ever teach ſuch impudent Doctrine as this; in <hi>Mahomet's Alcoran</hi> there is no abſurdity found like unto it.</p>
               <p>§ The great crowd of Martyrs, and the multitude of other Noble Saints, who have performed ſo many Miracles, and are challenged by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> as their
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:95424:20"/>own, was another powerful motive, to perſwade me of the Truth of their Faith, and of the Sanctity of their Religion. Who is it, ſaid I to my ſelf, that dares deny, that a Religion where ſo many Martyrs appear, that have laid down their Lives for Chriſt's Cauſe, where ſo many Saints have obſerved the Rules of the Goſpel, and made ſuch a glorious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of all Chriſtian Virtues; a Religion, where ſo many pious Souls do yet live a very exemplary and a holy life, having forſaken the World to confine themſelves to a Convent: Who dares deny ſuch a Religion to be the beſt, the ſecureſt, and the holieſt of all? In this manner I did argue, and many judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Perſons ſuffer themſelves to be thus deceived with a falſe appearance.</p>
               <p>But ſuch as will, as I have done, look more nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly to this particular, and weigh every thing in the Scales of the Sanctuary, ſhall find by experience, that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> hath no cauſe to glory ſo much in them. There are many Martyrs reckoned in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I confeſs, but this is no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible proof of its excellency: There have been many alſo in the Churches of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> of <hi>Antioch,</hi> of the <hi>Georgians, Muſcovites, Greeks, &amp;c.</hi> yet the <hi>Papiſts</hi> eſteem them not the more. But they ſay that many Saints in this Profeſſion have, and do yet per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form notable Miracles. I have cauſe to queſtion the truth of this Aſſertion, for many falſe ones are pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed; but when they ſhould be real, they are no infallible ſigns of the Truth of their Faith, for the Magicians of <hi>Egypt,</hi> by Gods permiſſion, did alſo work Miracles, <hi>Exod. chap.</hi> 7. God, whoſe Secrets and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:95424:20"/>Judgments are not to be ſearched out, may ſuffer the Devil to keep men in ignorance by this means. But the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay, that amongſt them many Religious Perſons are to be ſeen, that lead a moſt holy life. I anſwer, that they are for the moſt part but whited Sepulchres, and that this is the Devils cunning to deceive Souls. I ſhall ſay ſomething more in this Chapter. But what advantage do they expect from this Argument? There are men of honeſty every where, amongſt the Heathens and Hereticks as well as amongſt the Chriſtians and Catholicks there are perſons of good behaviour, or at leaſt appear ſo to the world. This is therefore no infallible ſign of a true Religion; but ſuppoſe it were ſo, that the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and integrity of life were an infallible ſign of the Truth, the <hi>Papiſts</hi> will never be able to better their Cauſe by this reaſon, unleſs their Chief and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, who are to be look'd upon as the Paterns of the reſt, change their manner of living. The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> is not ſo holy, as it is ſaid to be to the ſimple people, ignorant of the Affairs of that City. Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min the Tranſactions there now, and within this eight or nine hundred years. If we did but ſee the diſorders of this Church plainly preſented unto us, we ſhould have cauſe to wonder at the things related by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> themſelves of their Popes. I ſhall here mention ſome of them, and that I may not be tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced as a Lyar, I ſhall bring two or three of their own famous Writers ſpeaking of the Court of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſuch I mean who endeavour to cover its imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, and have never made uſe of their Pens but in its defence. The firſt is devout St. <hi>Bernard, Ser.</hi> 1.
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:95424:21"/>
                  <hi>de Converſ. Pauli:</hi> This man's integrity can never be ſuſpected. In this manner he ſpeaks of the Court of <hi>Rome: Iniquity proceeds from the grave Judges, who are named</hi> Chriſt's Vicegerents, <hi>and who ſeem to govern His people. Of them we cannot ſay,</hi> As is the People ſo is the Prieſt, <hi>for the people were not like or ſo bad as the Prieſt.</hi> And elſewhere, <hi>de Conſid. ad Eugen. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>From all parts of the world, the ambitious, the covetous, and perſons guilty of ſymony, ſacriledge, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauchery and inceſt, and ſuch like Monſters, did flock to</hi> Rome, <hi>to get the Eccleſiaſtical Honours, or to keep them by the</hi> Pope<hi>'s Authority.</hi> About the year 897, Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Baronius</hi> affirms, <hi>That there were the moſt wicked Varlets brought in to ſit in St.</hi> Peter<hi>'s Chair, men of moſt infamous lives, moſt fearfully debauch'd; of a corrupt and filthy behaviour, every where, and in every reſpect.</hi> And when he ſpeaks of the year 900, he intreats the weaker ſort of Chriſtians not to be offended from thenceforth, if they ſee ſometimes <hi>the abomination of deſolation in the Temple of God.</hi> Afterwards he cryes out: <hi>What horrible Monſters were introduced into this See, which the Angels reſpect? O diſgrace! O grief! how many evils have proceeded from them? how many grievous tragedies have been acted by them? what vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanies have been here committed in this glorious See? what filthy and baſe actions have appeared here? &amp;c.</hi> In the year 912, he ſaith, <hi>ſect.</hi> 8. this Church was ſo debauch'd and ſwimming in vice, <hi>That the filthieſt and the noted whores did govern all at</hi> Rome. <hi>At their pleaſure the See was diſpoſed of, the Biſhops were created, and their Favourites and Gallants were choſen in St.</hi> Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter<hi>'s Chair to be Popes.</hi> This is what <hi>Baronius</hi> hath
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:95424:21"/>been forced to acknowledge, after many other Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, who have recorded the diſorders of the <hi>Roman</hi> Church. Let any man read <hi>Genebrard. Chron. l.</hi> 4. <hi>ad ann.</hi> 902. <hi>Iſidor. Peleuſ. l.</hi> 3. <hi>epiſt.</hi> 323. <hi>Baptiſt. Mantuan. de calam. ſuorum temp. l.</hi> 3. <hi>Alvar. Pelag. de planctu Eccleſiae.</hi> Or let any man go to <hi>Rome,</hi> to ſee how ſuch behave themſelves, who pretend to be eſtabliſhed of God to govern His Church on earth; and they ſhall find there more wickedneſs than ever was in <hi>Sodom</hi> or in <hi>Nineveh. Let</hi> Rome <hi>be therefore aſhamed,</hi> ſaith a Learned Man who beheld theſe abominations, <hi>Claud. Eſpenſ. in Epiſt. ad Tit. c.</hi> 1. <hi>Let her never offer to ſhew a Catalogue of her ſhameful Crimes.</hi> I would adviſe her to not mention nor produce this Calendar of ſo many Saints, whom ſhe hath canoniſed, and in whom ſhe glories ſo much; for all thoſe former Saints diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover her ſhame, ſeeing that the Lives of the preſent Popes and Governours are quite contrary to theirs; therefore ſhe hath no cauſe to challenge them as her own. Thoſe former Worthies are her reproach and condemnation, becauſe ſhe doth not imitate their Example. Nevertheleſs the Popiſh Doctors are ſo impertinent, to boaſt of theſe diſorders, vices, and abominations, and to gather from thence reaſons to prove the truth and holineſs of their Religion. Who would believe that <hi>Baronius,</hi> after that he had filled his <hi>Annals</hi> with the filthy debaucheries of many Popes, ſhould gather from thence a concluſion to the advantage of his Church? Yet this he doth very boldly; for when he hath taken notice of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch'd and abominable Lives of ſome Popes, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared their vices in a moſt horrible manner, and
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:95424:22"/>acknowledged all that hath been written of them by his predeceſſors to be very true, that there have been Popes very <hi>ambitious, covetous, ſymoniacal, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, Murderers, lecherous, inceſtuous, Atheiſts,</hi> and <hi>Sodomites;</hi> which things the <hi>Papiſts</hi> cannot deny, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their own Hiſtorians declare them. Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, when <hi>Baronius</hi> hath ſaid all this of the Popes, he concludes, as boldly as if he had to prove the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity of Jeſus Chriſt, That all theſe Vices, by which St. <hi>Peter</hi>'s Chair hath been diſhonoured, are proofs of its Holineſs, Excellency, and Infallibility; becauſe, ſaith he, God hath permitted all theſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries and wickedneſſes in ſuch as were the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours of His Church without puniſhing them; this diſcovers that this Eſtate is more ſacred, more holy, and more regarded of God, than that of Kings, whom God commonly chaſtiſeth as ſoon as they are unfaithful and abuſe their Authority. I muſt needs confeſs, that I was never more aſtoniſhed, than when I found this Argument made uſe of by this Learned Man, and heard it approved of in the Popiſh Schools: Me thinks I could as eaſily prove the union of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traries to be found in the ſame Subject, as to ſhew the union and correſpondency of this Concluſion with the Principles from whence it is drawn. In this Church moſt abominable Popes have been ſeen. <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>var. Pelag.</hi> a <hi>Portugues</hi> Biſhop, tells us, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>art.</hi> 15. of many Popes, <hi>who have crept into that See by their factions, agreements, covenants, and large promiſes; and when they have got in, all their endeavour was to enrich and raiſe their Relations, to promote their friends to the chief Offices, to live themſelves in pleaſure, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:95424:22"/>to dignifie their Kindred, building Towers and Palaces in</hi> Babylon, <hi>I mean</hi> Rome, <hi>ſo called by St.</hi> Jerome. <hi>Theſe Popes have fomented the Wars and Factions in</hi> Italy, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of maintaining the unity of the Church: They have waſted the ſacred Revenues, advanced moſt unworthy per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and gloried in their chariots, elephants, horſes, rich garments, numerous train, guards, and noble attendants: They have by the power of the ſword often endeavoured to enlarge their own Borders, and ſeize upon the Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories of their neighbouring Princes, never minding the ſalvation of ſouls, but have been addicted to the pleaſures of the fleſh,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Theſe Men for money have ſold, as</hi> Judas <hi>did, Chriſt's Body, conſecrated the Sacraments, and celebrated Orders for ſilver,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>We have ſeen,</hi> (ſaith the ſame Author, <hi>lib.</hi> 2. <hi>art.</hi> 2. <hi>fol.</hi> 104.) <hi>men that have made this City like</hi> Sodom <hi>and</hi> Nineveh, <hi>by letting in, and countenancing all manner of vices, publick and private, as covetouſneſs, ambition, ſymony, uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pations, uncleanneſs, vain glory, envy, tyranny, and other crimes which cannot nor ought not to be named. We have ſeen in God's ſanctuary</hi> (ſaith the Biſhop of <hi>Bitonte,</hi> in the beginning of the Council of <hi>Trent, orat. hab. in concil. Trid. ſeſſ.</hi> 1.) <hi>ſhameleſs monſters, rotten veſſels full of infection, publick plagues,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſo that there remains no appearance nor hopes of good life, but an immoderate and extraordinary debauchery, a not able impudency, more crimes than can be well credited. We have ſeen</hi> (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the teſtimony of ſome Cardinals, choſen by Pope <hi>Paul III.</hi> for the Reformation of the Church, <hi>Concil. delect. Cardin. tom.</hi> 3. <hi>pag.</hi> 823.) <hi>Whores walking about the ſtreets of</hi> Rome <hi>as honourable Dames, carried upon Mules, attended and waited upon by Noblemen and
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:95424:23"/>Cardinals Chaplains, ſuch like ſcandals have never been ſeen elſewhere but in this City.</hi> We have ſeen (ſaith <hi>Guiſchardin,</hi> Hiſt. of <hi>Italy, lib.</hi> 1. <hi>ſect.</hi> 2.) <hi>Rodericus Borgia,</hi> who was afterwards Pope <hi>Alexander VI.</hi> buy the priviledge of diſpoſing of the Holy Treaſury. And <hi>Platina</hi> and <hi>Baronius</hi> relate, that there have been ſome Popes introduc'd by violence, who have clapp'd in priſon ſuch as were before in poſſeſſion of the See of <hi>Rome,</hi> as <hi>Chriſtopher</hi> did <hi>Leo VIII.</hi> Some have been ſo baſe and furious, that they have taken up the Bodies of their Predeceſſors, whoſe Fingers, wherewith they had given their bleſſing to the people, they have cut off and caſt into the <hi>Tybur,</hi> as <hi>Stephen VI.</hi> trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted <hi>Formoſus.</hi> In ſhort, we have ſeen men more co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous, ambitious, impious, lecherous, cruel, and wicked, than in the moſt licentious Courts, than amongſt the moſt barbarous Nations. And <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brard. Chron. lib.</hi> 4. ſaith, that theſe diſorders have laſted ſometimes 150 years together. During this time, ſaith <hi>Baronius, ann.</hi> 912. <hi>ſect.</hi> 8. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt ſlept very ſoundly in the bottom of the ſhip, and wink'd at all theſe miſchiefs.</hi> Therefore from hence he gathers this concluſion, for this cauſe the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> muſt needs be the trueſt, the holieſt, and beſt beloved of God, infallible, and the only Church that may be named <hi>Catholick, &amp;c.</hi> Let any man judge, if this be not the moſt impudent and unjuſt reaſoning in the world: The Heatheniſh Philoſophers have taught theſe Popiſh Doctors to argue in this manner for their Religion, from this ancient Maxim of theirs, <hi>Ex quolibet fit quodlibet:</hi> That from any Principle we may draw any Concluſion, either good or evil: They
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:95424:23"/>care not ſo they can but maintain their <hi>Theſis</hi> and Opinion; but theſe kind of Reaſons diſcover their weakneſs: For any Underſtanding may perceive from thence the feebleneſs of their Doctrine, the falſhood of their Religion, ſeeing that they are driven to draw ſuch Concluſions as are quite contrary to the nature and truth of the things themſelves. If any man ſay that this Reaſon is not in <hi>Baronius,</hi> word for word as I have expreſſed it; the premiſes are there, and the Concluſion, not in two or three words, and in ſuch a plain and ſuccinct manner as I have here related it, but it is laid down in a more ample, and more florid Diſcourſe, which tends to no other end, but to prove the Truth, Holineſs, and Excellency of of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Religion, from the Vices and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baucheries of its Prieſts and Popes. This cannot but be look'd upon as very ridiculous by any man of Judgement. For if their Reaſons were good, I might as well ſay that <hi>Pharaoh</hi>'s Kingdom was holy, becauſe God ſuffered it to continue ſo long without puniſhing him, and did many Miracles for his ſake; and that the <hi>Turkiſh</hi> Religion muſt needs be the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieſt and the beſt at preſent, becauſe God hath ſuffered it to abide ſo many years, and increaſe every day, although its Chieftains lead moſt filthy lives.</p>
               <p>Theſe and ſuch like Conſiderations, which I have had by reading the Books of the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Doctors and Hiſtorians, have leſſened that vaſt eſteem that I had formerly for that Church, and made me to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that all its excellent Priviledges which it claims, and which they aſſign to her, are but whimſeys and <hi>Chimaera's</hi> begot in their fancy by their
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:95424:24"/>fondneſs for their Religion, the Popes ambition, and the credulity of ſilly minds, who are ready to believe any thing, the greateſt abſurdity, if boldly aſſerted. Let us proceed next to our other Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>THE SECOND PART.</head>
               <p>THE Second Reaſon that hath ſo long time kept my Mind in a ballance, was grounded upon the Faith and Articles of that Church. I did ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly examine all thoſe things which ſhe engageth us to believe as infallible Truths; the Pope's Infal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>libility, the real and corporal preſence of Jeſus Chriſt in the Sacrament of the Altar, the Sacrifice of the Maſs, Purgatory, the Invocation of Saints, and the certain damnation of all thoſe who acknowledge not the Pope for their Superiour, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I thought all this to be very true, when I look'd upon it with the Popiſh Spectacles which they give to all that read their Writings, or ſtudy in their Schools; and judged this Church to be the beſt and holieſt. Hath not Jeſus Chriſt ſaid, I have promiſed to St. <hi>Peter, that his Faith ſhould never fail?</hi> doth not he mean that his Succeſſors ſhould be always <hi>Infallible?</hi> hath he not ſaid in celebrating his Holy Supper, that the Bread was his <hi>Body,</hi> and the Wine his <hi>Blood,</hi> expreſly, and in proper terms? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> In this manner I did argue upon all the Articles of the Popiſh Faith, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluding always to its advantage.</p>
               <p>But when I had more narrowly Examined theſe matters alone, without partiality, I found that I was
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:95424:24"/>very far from Truth; that all theſe Articles of Faith were not conformable to Holy Scripture, but alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether contrary; and the Popiſh Religion oppoſite to that of Jeſus Chriſt, of the Apoſtles, and of the Primitive Fathers.</p>
               <p>§. For where ſhall we find any thing of the Pope's Infallibility in the Holy Scripture? ſhall not we find rather, that the holieſt of men <hi>are liars?</hi> Pſal. 115. 11. and 61.10. <hi>That we fail all in many things, and that if any man fails not in word, he may boaſt of being a perfect man.</hi> Jam. 3. and St. <hi>John</hi> informs us, that we are all Sinners. Moreover, this Infallibility is according to the judgment of the Popiſh Doctors, one of its Divine Attributes, ſtiled by them Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicable, how can they therefore ſay that God hath given it to a man? and why to the Pope of all other men? ſeeing that according to the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists</hi> confeſſion, he is many times a very wicked man. And St. <hi>Peter</hi> himſelf, unto whom the Son of God had promiſed that his Faith ſhould never fail, from whence they would eſtabliſh this Doctrine, was guilty of a great miſtake concerning the Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the <hi>Jews</hi> and Gentiles, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> affirms, <hi>I have reſiſted him to his face,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for he was to be blamed.</hi> Is it poſſible, that the Pope, choſen by a company of men who know not whom they pitch upon, and promoted many times by Legerdemain, by Bribes, ſubtilty, temporal Intereſts, Princes fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours? Is it poſſible, that theſe Popes, who are
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:95424:25"/>to be all <hi>Italians</hi> born, elected out of the number of Cardinals, and ſo aged, that they can ſcarce do any good, but by others? Is it poſſible that theſe Popes, promoted by the aſſiſtance of Whores, and the Cardinals Courtizans, as <hi>Paronius</hi> and <hi>Bellarmin,</hi> and others acknowledge, ſhould be more infallible than St. <hi>Peter,</hi> choſen by Chriſt himſelf? How can we imagin that ſuch a man ſhould be a Treaſury intruſted with Divine knowledge and the will of God? that his voice pronounced out of his Chair, ſhould be the voice of Heaven; that he ſhould be able to cauſe the Holy Ghoſt to go and come at his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure; and to oblige God to ratifie and confirm all his Laws in the World, to command when he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, to prohibit when he prohibits, to damn when he damns, and to ſave when he ſaith the word! Before we can believe this, they muſt deprive us of our judgments, and make us become beaſts before we can become Chriſtians, and deal with us worſe than <hi>Mahomet</hi> deals with his <hi>Muſſulmans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Pope, being aſſiſted by ſome of his Brethren, hath pronounced the Sentence, which they ſay is, <hi>ex Cathedra,</hi> and condemned <hi>Janſenius</hi> and his fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers, he hath declared them to be Hereticks; muſt I believe it as an Article of Faith? becauſe he ſaith, that in the Book of this Learned Biſhop there are five Propoſitions, the ſame as were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned heretofore in <hi>Calvin,</hi> and that only from the information of the holy Fathers the <hi>Jeſuits:</hi> Muſt I take all this as an Article of my Faith; although Mr. <hi>Arnaldus,</hi> and other Doctors of the Port-Royal have proved to all that can but read, that theſe
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:95424:25"/>Propoſitions are not be found in his Books. The Pope ſaith that <hi>Peter d'Acantara, Francis de Sales,</hi> and <hi>Pius V.</hi> are He-Saints in Heaven; that <hi>Mary Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delen</hi> of <hi>Pazzi,</hi> Mother <hi>Roſe,</hi> and others, are She-Saints; he commands us to pray to them: If I doubt of it, and ſpeak as the wiſe Son of <hi>Sirach,</hi> Eccl. 9. whoſe Book is received amongſt the Canonical, <hi>That no body knows whether he be worthy of love or hatred,</hi> much leſs doth he know this of others: if I ſhould ſay as the Goſpel, that it belongs to God to judge men, and <hi>that all Judgment is left unto Jeſus Christ;</hi> or as St. <hi>Paul, that the Judgments of God are unſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,</hi> and that therefore I leave it to him; I am an Heretick amongſt the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Since theſe He and She-Saints have been Canonized, it is become an Article of Faith to believe them in Heaven: Before I was at my own choice, to credit what I pleaſed; but ſince that time I am no longer free, the Pope hath ſaid it, we muſt therefore believe it: if I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe their Mediation, if I neglect to pray to them, out of a diſtruſt of their happineſs and credit with God; I am an Infidel, and an Athieſt, in the judgment of the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Is not this to mock God and men?</p>
               <p>Some of them anſwer, that the Pope may erre <hi>in matters of fact, but not in matters of right,</hi> Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min. <hi>de Po. l.</hi> 4. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. But we all know that moſt of their queſtions of right depend upon matters of Fact; and that the judgment of right, which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns not only the Doctrines of the Holy Scripture, but an infinit number of other things received by Tradition, proceeds from the teſtimony and infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:95424:26"/>which they have received of ſeveral matters of Fact. Suppoſe therefore that all theſe informations ſhould be falſe, as they may be; for the Pope, who only is to be look'd upon as Infallible, according to the <hi>Papists</hi> Doctrine, hath not ſeen all theſe things, he believes it from the teſtimony of others. For Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; It is an Article of Faith amongſt them, that St. <hi>Peter hath been twenty five years Biſhop of</hi> Rome; that he hath added the word <hi>enim</hi> to the words of the Conſecration, ſaying, <hi>Hoc eſt enim corpus meum;</hi> and not as it is in the Goſpel, <hi>Hoc eſt corpus meum:</hi> that he did <hi>mingle Water with the Wine,</hi> in the Maſs. If theſe things, that are all matters of fact, which cannot be proved by Holy Scripture, be falſe, as we have cauſe to imagin, what certainty can we have of the right and truth which depends upon it?</p>
               <p>§ Moreover, I find the <hi>Papists</hi> Sacrament of the Lords Supper differing very much from the deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption which Chriſt and his Apoſtles have left us. It is <hi>the bread of life,</hi> ſay the <hi>Romaniſts, the bread of Angels, the Heavenly bread, the Body and Bloud of Jeſus Christ:</hi> I have always believed it to be ſo, I think there is no good Chriſtian that doubts of it. We all know that it is no <hi>common Bread,</hi> no body will contradict them in this, St. <hi>Juſtin</hi> ſhall not be condemned for affirming it. That the Bread be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes the <hi>Body</hi> of Chriſt, and the Wine his <hi>Blood,</hi> &amp;c. all this is well and very true, we are not ignorant that St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> St. <hi>Cyril</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:95424:26"/>of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and many other ancient Doctors name it ſo. But how can the <hi>Papists</hi> ſhew by the Holy Scripture that Chriſt is there, in the ſame manner as they affirm, by a real preſence, which is not only ſpiritual, but material and corporal? That he is there in the ſame manner as he was of old in the Virgins womb, in the manger of <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> upon Mount <hi>Tabor,</hi> and upon the Croſs, and nevertheleſs that he is in the higheſt Heavens, at the right hand of God the Father? Where can they find in all the four Evangeliſts any Text that mentions this prodigious Miracle of the <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> or tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mutation of the bread into the real Body of Jeſus Chriſt, and of the wine into his Blood, with a deſtruction of the firſt, and a creation of the latter, by the efficacy of four words uttered by a Prieſt? Where is there a Writer of the <hi>Greek,</hi> or of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Latin</hi> Church, that ſpeaks of this Myſtery in the ſame manner as <hi>Thomas Aquinas;</hi> who main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained <hi>a corporal preſence multiplied, without diviſion; accidents ſuſtained without their proper ſubſtance; a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continuance of a being, without corruption; a production of the ſame effects by a cauſe that is not; an humane and divine ſubſtance under the appearance of a Wafer; a God made man, where nothing of his manhood is to be ſeen; a body without extenſion; a life without motion; an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite number of equal parts, proportionable to their</hi> totum <hi>in a Mathematical point; a relation from the ſame to the ſame, from the first to a ſecond, who are but one; a ſituation without ſpace; an abiquity without place; a general deſtruction of all Predicaments by this ſuppoſed Myſtery,</hi> or <hi>Manhu,</hi> as he calls it? a word which
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:95424:27"/>expreſſeth the admiration of the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> when they ſaw the <hi>Manna</hi> fall amongſt them. Did ever St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> or any of the four chief Doctors of the Chriſtian Church ſpeak in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner? they did never imagine that ſo many abſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities could enter into the minds of men. I am perſwaded, that if this Doctor, ſtiled by them the Angelick Doctor, becauſe of the rare Inventions of his Wit, had lived in the days of St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and had ſpoken unto him in theſe terms, that Primitive Father would never have underſtood him, although he underſtood the Predicaments of <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> without Tutor: doubtleſs he had taken him for a man faln from the Clouds, dwelling in the Globe of the Moon, or for one that maintains that there is there another World.</p>
               <p>Where have they ſeen in Holy Scripture, or amongſt the ancient Fathers, <hi>That the Lay-men muſt not communicate in both kinds; that the Maſs is a Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice where the Paſſion of our Saviour is really renewed; that Jeſus Christ will be there worſhipped in a viſible manner, by an adoration that relates to the ſubstances, as God himſelf, if he were to be ſeen;</hi> according to the Command of the Council of <hi>Trent?</hi> I have been ſeveral years reading and peruſing the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures and its Interpreters, but I have found nothing there like to theſe Doctrines, unleſs it be in the Popiſh Authors; for I have met with an hundred paſſages contrary to this belief. I confeſs we find in Holy Writ that Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>This is my Body;</hi> but he hath ſaid alſo, <hi>I am the Door, I am the Stone, I am the Vine, and the Shepherd of the Sheep,</hi> &amp;c.
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:95424:27"/>If we are to take all theſe expreſſions in a literal ſonſe, we muſt believe that he is a <hi>Door,</hi> a <hi>Stone,</hi> a <hi>Vine,</hi> a <hi>Shepherd of Sheep.</hi> But the Scripture ſaith that <hi>Jeſus Chriſt is aſcended up into Heaven, and that he ſits there at the right hand of God the Father.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he is no longer upon Earth; for it is not poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble that the ſame Body ſhould be in two diſtinct places at once: If that were likely, as the Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers tell us, the ſame Body might be in twenty, in an hundred, in a thouſand, and in ten thouſand places in the ſame moment: From hence we might con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, that it is poſſible to make one man become a great Army; that one man ſhould kill himſelf a thouſand times, and yet continue alive; that he ſhould be a Saint in one place, and a Devil in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; damned in one place, and ſaved in another; the object of Gods wrath and goodneſs at the ſame time: theſe are impoſſibilities, and plain contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions. Chriſt commands us <hi>to do this in Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of Him;</hi> therefore he is not there really and bodily; for we do nothing in remembrance of a man preſent before us in a corporal manner. The <hi>Papists</hi> inſtance the <hi>Manna,</hi> which was kept by God's command in the Ark, in remembrance of that which God ſent down from Heaven; which was both the remembrance, and the thing remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred; the repreſentation, and the thing repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. This is one of the moſt plauſible Examples of the <hi>Papists,</hi> but it is to little purpoſe; for be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides other Reaſons that may be alledged againſt it, I think they are mightily miſtaken, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare a <hi>totum integrans</hi> with an <hi>individual</hi> one; and
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:95424:28"/>the ſame may be divided, and the parts carried into ſeveral diſtinct places, where they may be look'd upon in divers manners; but the other is altogether repugnant to diviſion and ſeparation. The <hi>Manna</hi> that was in the Ark, I confeſs, was a memorial of that <hi>Manna</hi> which the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> had fed upon in the Wilderneſs, but it was not the ſame. How can they therefore from hence conclude, that Chriſt's body muſt be in ſeveral places under diſtinct notions? <hi>Christ</hi> informs us, <hi>That His words are ſpirit and life; and that the fleſh profiteth nothing; that it is the ſpirit that quickens.</hi> It is not poſſible to ſpeak any thing more contrary than this, to the <hi>Papists</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine; for theſe words aſſure us that Chriſt is there really, and in truth, but <hi>ſpiritually,</hi> not <hi>corporally,</hi> nor <hi>ſubſtantially;</hi> that He is there by his Spirit, virtue, and efficacy, to produce the ſame effects in us as if he were there in a ſenſible manner. This was taught by the Primitive Fathers, and thus the <hi>Protestants</hi> believe it. He commands us alſo <hi>To eat his Fleſh, and drink his Blood,</hi> in both kinds: St. <hi>Paul</hi> repeats the words; and the Council of <hi>Conſtance,</hi> which is eſteemed by the <hi>Papiſts</hi> as highly as a fift Evangil, ſaith that ſince the Apoſtles time Communicants did receive in both kinds; wherefore did they then take away the Cup? why did they eſtabliſh this Law, that forbids Lay-men to drink of the Cup? They acknowledge, that Jeſus Chriſt hath appointed it to be ſo; that the Apoſtles did practice and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it; and that it had been an univerſal cuſtom amongſt Chriſtians, for all men to communicate in both kinds. Nevertheleſs this Council was ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:95424:28"/>to forbid it, and command the World to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that this Prohibition proceeds from the Holy Ghoſt, although it be contrary to Chriſt's Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, to the Apoſtles Doctrine, and the Practice of the firſt Chriſtians; we muſt have a notable Faith to believe this. The inconveniencies which they mention to colour their Change are ridiculous. They tell us, that ſome men wear long Beards, and that a drop of Chriſt's Blood may chance to drop upon them; and that ſome that are ſick may by this means give their Diſeaſes to others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But how comes it to paſs that Jeſus Chriſt did not foreſee all theſe inconveniencies? were the Biſhops of this Council wiſer than Chriſt himſelf? Did not the men of our Saviour's days, and in the Primitive time wear long Beards? were they not as ſubject to ſpreading Diſeaſes, as well as in the time of this Council? St. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us that Jeſus Chriſt hath offered himſelf up <hi>once for all,</hi> as a Sacrifice; but they affirm that he offers himſelf not only once, but every day, and a thouſand times a day, and in a thouſand diſtinct places, in every corner where the Maſs is ſung, which is, ſay they, <hi>a true and real Sacrifice of the Body of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> Whom muſt we believe? what the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſay? or what St. <hi>Paul?</hi> But ſuppoſe the Maſs were a true and real Sacrifice of Jeſus Chriſt, a ſecond death, and his very Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as they teach; are not their Prieſts Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derers and Executioners? from whence proceeds this effect? is it not from a real cauſe that is in them? Whence is this Sacrifice, is it not from a true and real Sacrificator? Moreover, according
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:95424:29"/>to their own Doctrine, three conditions are chiefly required in every Sacrifice, the Offering, the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecration, and the Deſtruction; where ſhall they find the latter in this Sacrifice of the Maſs? Do they deſtroy the Body of Jeſus Chriſt? if they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, that they deſtroy the Bread and the Wine, they don't anſwer to the queſtion; for it muſt be the Sacrifice that muſt be conſumed and deſtroyed; for either we muſt ſay that only the Bread and the Wine are ſacrificed, or that the Body of Jeſus Chriſt is there deſtroyed and conſumed: Hence we muſt conclude, that he is both dying and immortal, dead and riſen, and worſhipped by the Angels, and at the ſame time eaten by Men, things altogether inconſiſtent and impoſſible. But where do they find that we muſt worſhip the Bread and the Wine, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing united to the Body of Jeſus Chriſt? that we muſt kneel at every time that we ſee them, as before God himſelf, if he were viſibly preſent? Doth not Jeſus Chriſt command the contrary, when he ſaith, that the time is come that we muſt worſhip God <hi>in ſpirit and in truth?</hi> How in ſpirit, if we worſhip the Bread and the Wine? How in truth, if Jeſus Chriſt be not there really preſent? as we have good cauſe to queſtion it, and as it may happen, according to their own ſaying. For in caſe the Prieſt be not a true Prieſt, in regard of ſome Canonical impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; or if his intention be elſewhere in celebrating Maſs, what kind of Maſs will it be? and what ſhall the People adore? Some young men come to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive Orders very much unprepared, whom the Lord Biſhop ſaith that he hath no deſign to receive and
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:95424:29"/>admit to the Prieſthood: as for example, when they ſend other perſons in their ſtead, that are more Learned, to be examined for them; when they make uſe of falſe and ſuppoſed Letters; when they are mentioned in a Decree, or deſerve an Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation. All theſe perſons, according to the Popiſh Doctors, are not really Prieſts; they have not the power to make the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, although they may pronounce the words of the Sacrament. Others have not a right intention, out of negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence or deſign, theſe cannot cauſe Jeſus Chriſt to come down under the <hi>ſpecies</hi> of the Bread and the Wine, although they pronounce the words of the Conſecration. I have known a Prieſt, that cauſed a noble Dame to Receive almoſt every day, at the end of his Maſs, to hide from her Husband the ſecret correſpondency that was between them, and to cover it over with a fair ſhew of Devotion; and for four or five years he never gave unto her a conſecrated Wafer, for fear of committing Sacriledge, by cauſing her to receive in an evil diſpoſition. And about ſix months ago, ſome Prieſts of a Town where I have dwelt, to ſatisfie a devout Woman faln into Frenzy, that did earneſtly deſire them to admit her to the Communion, reſolved amongſt themſelves to put an unconſecrated Wafer into the Chalice, which ſhould be ſeparate from the reſt. In ſuch a caſe, I deſire you the Divines of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to tell me, if you believe that Jeſus Chriſt is not preſent in the Bread and Wine but when the Prieſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth his words with an intention to make him come down from Heaven, whether the people that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:95424:30"/>aſſiſt there and worſhip the Wafers, don't commit a grievous Idolatry? Yes, you will ſay, they commit a material Idolatry: But pray tell, whether the Prieſt and the penitent Woman, the Whoremaſter and the Whore, did not commit a crime in your judgment? was not this as great and as formal an Idolatry as ever was ſeen? I ſhall not mention many other ſtories of the baſeneſs, Sacriledges, and Ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latries of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſts, which they are guilty of in this occaſion; for I intend not to make a ſaty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rical Libel of this ſerious Diſcourſe. I ſhall only ſay in general terms, that if the Father-Confeſſors of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would but ſpeak truth, and declare what I have heard, there is no reaſonable man of any perſwaſion, but will ſay that which we cannot utter without blaſphemy, that Jeſus Chriſt would be extravagant and mad, if he were in the Maſs, as the Papiſts believe.</p>
               <p>§. Purgatory is another new Article of their Creed, which hath no ground nor appearance in Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture. The <hi>Papists</hi> mention a certain place out of the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> Book 2. ch. 12. v. 43. but this Book St. <hi>Jerom, praefat. in Proverb.</hi> and many more, as <hi>Cajetan, in fine Comment, in hiſt. Eſther,</hi> and Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Hugo, in Prolog. Hier. in lib. Regum,</hi> declare to be Apocrypha. Another paſſage is cited out of St. <hi>Matth.</hi> 12. where Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, that there are ſome Sins that <hi>ſhall not be pardoned, neither in this world, nor in the world to come:</hi> From hence the <hi>Papiſts</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:95424:30"/>conclude by a Maxim of Right, <hi>Exceptio firmat regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam in contrarium;</hi> that there are ſome Sins that ſhall be pardoned in another world, that is to ſay, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their meaning, in Purgatory. But we may eaſily perceive that they miſerably wreſt this paſſage, and argue very impertinently to make this concluſion; <hi>Some Sins ſhall neither be pardoned in this world, nor in the world to come;</hi> ergo, <hi>There is a Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory.</hi> A Chymiſt would ſooner extract ten ounces of Oyl out of a Pumice-ſtone, than to gather this concluſion from the premiſſes: But there is nothing impoſſible to the Popiſh Divines; they can make a fire with any wood, when they are to warm their own Kitchin. If I might argue in the ſame manner, I might ſay with more reaſon, that <hi>Judas Maccha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baeus</hi> never thought to ſpeak of Purgatory in the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going paſſage, but of the Reſurrection of the dead: I am perſwaded, that from St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s words, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>He hath by himſelf purged our Sins;</hi> we may conclude a Doctrine contrary to this of the <hi>Papiſts;</hi> For ſeeing Chriſt hath purged our Sins, what need of any other Purgatory; ſeeing that he hath done this by himſelf, that is, by his Blood, as St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>Revelat.</hi> 1.6. there is no need of the Fire of Purgatory.</p>
               <p>But pray tell me which of all the firſt Doctors of the Chriſtian Church mentions Purgatory? and how was that Feſtival eſtabliſhed in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to pray to God for the deceaſed? I have many times been aſhamed, when I have been queſtioned, becauſe I was forced to alledge a Dream as the cauſe and ground of one of the chief Articles of that Religion.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:95424:31"/>The Abbot of one of the Monaſteries of St. <hi>Benedictus,</hi> as the <hi>Roman</hi> Legend declares, heard upon the top of a Mountain from whence certain flames did proceed, not much unlike to thoſe of <hi>Aetna</hi> and <hi>Veſuvius,</hi> a confuſion of voices; occaſioned by the ſtrugling of the flames with the air round about, as the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophers inform us; as many times it happens when the Air is ſhut up in Rocks and concavities: this brain-ſick Abbot fancied that theſe voices came from the departed Souls burning in thoſe flames, to deſire his Prayers. Therefore he appointed in his Convent a Feſtival-day, to pray to God for the deliverance of theſe poor Sufferers. The next night it is ſaid that he had a viſion of theſe Souls, which to his ſeeming were mounting apace towards Heaven at the ſame time that his Monks were praying in their Church for them. Afterwards he publiſhed his Dream and Viſion, which was look'd upon as a Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation; when the Pope came to underſtand it, he ſoon eſtabliſhed a Feſtival, like that of the Abbot and Monks in their Convent, to be obſerved all over Chriſtianity: The deſign ſucceeded very happily; the ſilly women, that believed that their husbands Souls were frying in Purgatory, gave vaſt ſumms of Money, and great Revenues, that Prayers might be ſaid for the happineſs of the deceaſed. About this time ſome Dreamers had Viſions in their ſleep, the Prieſts aſſſured them that their departed Friends did require from them Prayers; this Doctrine was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed in the Pulpits, and believed every whereas an undoubted Truth; it paſs'd for an Article of Faith, for which the Prieſts were more willing to dye, than
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:95424:31"/>for the Faith of one God, or for the belief of the Incarnation of the Son of God. This was the firſt beginning of that Feſtival, and of that mode re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived for currant in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> to pray to God for the deceaſed Souls. From hence we may judg of the thing in it ſelf; and whether it is not to the abuſe of mens credulity, to deliver upon theſe grounds this as an Article of Faith.</p>
               <p>But, that we may refute the <hi>Papists</hi> Errours from their own confeſſions and belief, If we may obtain <hi>a full Indulgence</hi> to be exempt from the flames of Purgatory; if by wearing a <hi>little Scapulary,</hi> a <hi>Medal of five Saints,</hi> or by repeating three times in our ſickneſs <hi>Jeſu Maria</hi> before a Crucifix, or by being of the Fraternities of the the <hi>little Habit of the Virgin,</hi> or of the <hi>Roſary,</hi> or of the <hi>Dying:</hi> What reaſon have they to be ſo earneſt with the Widows, that Prayers may be ſaid for their Husbands? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> when they have ſeen them perform all theſe duties which they impoſe upon the negligent, as weighty Caſes of Conſcience, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially at the time of Confeſſion, what need of any Maſs to be ſaid for their deliverance from Purgatory? They affirm at <hi>Rome,</hi> that one Maſs ſaid before a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledged Altar is able to bring up a Soul from the very bottom of Purgatory, although it hath been condemned to remain there one hundred or a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand years, or till the day of Judgment: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore then do they oblige Children to buy daily Maſſes for many years in all the Churches of a City, and give away their Revenues for ever, for the repoſe and happineſs of their Parents Souls? If one Maſs be ſufficient, what need is there of ſo many thouſands?
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:95424:32"/>wherefore do they condemn them as Atheiſts that will have but One, becauſe they truſt upon the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge of ſuch Altars? And if the Pope hath the power to let the Souls go out of Purgatory when he pleaſeth, as the <hi>Papists</hi> ſay, why does he not free them? Is it not for want of Charity, to ſuffer them there in Torments? to releaſe but one, when he may releaſe a thouſand, or all. Is it not pity to ſee needy wretches labour and ſweat all the Week long; poor Widows take the Bread out of their Childrens mouths, before they come to be of age, and give it to a fat Prieſt on the Sunday, that he might ſay a Maſs, and deliver by that means from Purgatory the Soul of a Wife or of an Husband, when the Pope may perform this with two words, by granting an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence? From hence we may plainly diſcover that the chief deſign of this was to enrich the Clergy with the ſpoils of the Orphelin, and of the poor Widows, and with the Eſtate of the deceaſed.</p>
               <p>§. The Invocation of Saints is another ſenſleſs and groundleſs Doctrine; for there is no Text of Holy Scripture that mentions any thing of it: it is there neither commanded nor allowed of, nay ſeveral paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges prohibit this Idolatry: <hi>There is one God,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Paul, and one Mediator between God and men, the man Christ Jeſus,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.5. there he confirms the Faith of <hi>one God, and of one Mediator:</hi> If any ſhould offer to maintain to a Popiſh Doctor that there are many Gods, he would exclaim in a rage upon him,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:95424:32"/>as upon a wicked Idolater: Fair and ſoft, Mr. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, you have little cauſe to ſuffer your wrath to kindle againſt a perſon as innocent as your ſelf; you are no leſs guilty, in regard that you affirm that there be many Mediators, although St. <hi>Paul</hi> proteſts that there is but <hi>one,</hi> as there is but <hi>one God.</hi> The King of <hi>Samaria</hi> was puniſhed with death, becauſe he had ſent to enquire of the god of <hi>Ekron,</hi> as if there had been no God in <hi>Iſrael.</hi> The <hi>Papists</hi> deſerve as great a puniſhment, becauſe Chriſt hath been pleaſed to invite us unto himſelf, and oblige us to ſeek to him alone; <hi>Come unto me all ye that travel and are heavy laden, and I will refreſh you: learn of me, for I am meek and lowly,</hi> Matth. 11.28. No, replies a <hi>Papist,</hi> I will not go to thee, I will not addreſs my ſelf directly to thee; for thou art a rigorous God, thou wilt not ſuffer Sinners to be ſo bold to ſpeak to thee, only Saints are allowed to offer up unto thee their Prayers. Doth not this language of a <hi>Papist</hi> contradict Chriſt's command, and ſlight his call and gracious deſign? When the Son of God came into the World, he had no other intention but to baniſh out of it all Idolatry, and to eſtabliſh the Worſhip of the true God. Becauſe, ſaith an Eloquent Biſhop of <hi>Ravenna,</hi> that wonderful Majeſty in which God appeared unto <hi>Moſes,</hi> and the dreadful threatnings and puniſhments of his Law did hinder his people to make their addreſſes to, and truſt in him, and did encourage Idolatry, by cauſing them to ſeek to other gods, more tractable, and of a more eaſie acceſs; he hath been pleaſed to become Man, like unto us, <hi>To win them by the expreſſions of his kindneſs, and to hold
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:95424:33"/>them fast bound to his ſervice, by the testimonies and declarations of his Goodneſs,</hi> Petr. Chryſol. <hi>Ser.</hi> 147. This was God's deſign: But by that ſtrange propen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of men to Idolatry, they hinder its accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; for inſtead of looking up to him, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving from him grace and mercy, they have run to others, and ſought for other Mediators and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tectors, other viſible Gods, whom they implore in their indigency: This alienation from God proceeds from their fancying him who is their Brother, and like unto them, and who is become their Friend, armed with ſeverity and juſtice; by this means they are frighted away from his ſervice, and cannot with ſo much confidence as they ought rely upon his Mercy. In this manner God's divine Wiſdom is diſappointed, and his Deſign fruſtrated by the ignorance, baſeneſs, and blindneſs of men. The Intent of the Son of God, ſaith <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary ſtrain, when he took upon him our nature, was totally to aboliſh Idolatry; he knew that men were very inclinable to this vice, that few in the world would be content to worſhip God in ſpirit and in truth; he had ſeen them bow down to a golden Calf, to mortal Men, to Statues of ſtone, Onions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is an Impudency, ſaith likewiſe St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> which was unſufferable to him; he had an intent to bring a remedy to theſe diſorders, by condeſcending a little to mens inclinations; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he took upon him a Body, that men might have a God according to their own mind and deſires, and that they might adore a Man without offence: <hi>Ut pro impudentia idololatriae ſatis Deo fieret per impudentiam
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:95424:33"/>fidei.</hi> How did men anſwer ſo great a Mercy? I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs they prayed unto, and worſhipped this God-Man very faithfully for ſeveral Ages; but at laſt the Spirit of darkneſs crept in amongſt them, and hath drawn ſome away to their former Abominations: inſtead of being governed by that holy Impudency which Faith furniſhes them with, and prompts them to, to adore God in a Saviour-Man, and worſhip a man as God; they have ſubſtituted others in whom they confide, to whom they preſent their Vows, and offer their Sacrifices. This is the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Crime: Jeſus Chriſt is not properly their God, they worſhip and pray to the Saints; they forſake the Lord, that calls and invites them to come to him, to go and make their Prayers to, and worſhip the Servants. Look but into their Chappels and Churches, you ſhall ſcarce ſee ten perſons kneeling to the Crucifix, when you may perceive ſeveral hundreds before the Altars of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> and of the other Saints: I have often taken notice of this when I was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them. I am perſwaded, that if the <hi>Papiſts</hi> had not their Idol of the Maſs, I mean the Sacrament, to preſent to the people to receive their homages, Jeſus Chriſt, whom this Sacrament ſignifies, would be quite forgotten; they would ſcarce think upon him, if they did, it would be with much indifferency. You ſhall ſee ſomething more of this in the next Article.</p>
               <p>§. The Worſhipping of Images is one of thoſe things that was moſt offenſive to me in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:95424:34"/>ſince I took the liberty to read the Holy Scripture; for I never found any one paſſage that ſeems to allow this Superſtition, but have met with many that repreſent it as the moſt grievous of all other crimes. I know that their ingenious Wits have diſtinguiſhed their Worſhip into that of <hi>Latria,</hi> which is only due unto God; and into <hi>Dulia</hi> and <hi>Hyperdulia,</hi> which may be paid to the Creature: But how can the igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant Vulgar make this diſtinction? And doth not God in expreſs words prohibit, in one of the Ten Commandments written with his divine finger in the Tables of ſtone delivered to <hi>Moſes</hi> upon the Mountain, <hi>To make any Image, or likeneſs of things which are in Heaven or elſewhere;</hi> and command us, <hi>not to fall down to them, nor ſerve them?</hi> Do not the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts</hi> by their daily practices violate this Sacred Law? To what purpoſe are their cunning diſtinctions, and the right direction of their intentions, their ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vations of their mind from the Image to the Saint, and from the Saint unto God, ſeeing they do what God hath expreſly forbidden? I deſire to convince the moſt obſtinate of all the <hi>Papiſts</hi> by their own thoughts, and the reflexion of their minds, for this conſideration hath been very powerful to undeceive me. When I did conſider the continual diſputes between <hi>Protestants</hi> and <hi>Papists</hi> about the worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping of Images, I thought upon St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s words, to <hi>Petil.</hi> and the reſt of the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and that his direction was the beſt means to end the controverſie, and to underſtand which of them was in the right, <hi>To.</hi> 7. <hi>de unit. Eccleſ. contr. Epiſt. Petil. c.</hi> 3. <hi>Non audia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur haec dico, haec dicis, ſed haec dicit Dominus,</hi> &amp;c. we
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:95424:34"/>muſt not heed what the <hi>Protestants</hi> ſay, nor what the <hi>Papists</hi> affirm; but only what God declares, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the expoſition of thoſe Doctors that were of neither ſide: let us take one of them, or if the judgment of one is not ſufficient, let us take ten, put into their hands that by which we ſhall all be judged, the two Tables delivered to <hi>Moſes,</hi> the ten Commandments of God, let us intreat them to read over that which concerns the Worſhipping of Images; <hi>Thou ſhalt not make unto thy ſelf any graven Image, or the likeneſs of any thing that is in heaven above, or that is in the earth beneath, or that is in the water under the earth, thou ſhalt not how down thy ſelf to them, nor ſerve them; for I the Lord thy God am a jealous God, viſiting the iniquity,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Exod.</hi> 20. Let us lead theſe indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent men into a Church of the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and into ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the <hi>Reformed Religion,</hi> let us deſire them to tell us which of theſe Perſwaſions is to their ſeeming moſt conformable and obedient to this Law: will they not ſay that it is the <hi>Reformed</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant?</hi> For amongſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> they may ſee ſeveral Churches and Chappels, and in each of them eight or ten Saints, or rather Images of Saints, and before every one of theſe Images they ſhall find above twenty men and women kneeling with lighted Tapers in their hands, they ſhall ſee others carrying their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings up to the Saints Altars, and a Prieſt in his Maſs, often perfuming the noſe of the Image with Incenſe, they ſhall ſee a Deacon appointed to read the Goſpel, reading that appointed for the Saint's day, over the head of ſuch diſeaſed perſons as they imagin that the Saint can cure, they ſhall ſee many
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:95424:35"/>others, as well Prieſts as other Clerks, ſinging upon their knees the Litanies of that Saint before the dumb Image, and ſuch like abominations they ſhall ſee. What think ye in conſcience that theſe Primitive Doctors would ſay if they beheld all this foppery? would they not cry out againſt that which God hath prohibited? You are in the Errour, would they ſay to the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> for ye do what God hath forbidden in expreſs words: He forbids you <hi>to make Images,</hi> and your Churches are full of them: He forbids you <hi>to make any Likeneſs of any thing that is in Heaven above,</hi> and nevertheleſs you make un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to your ſelves the Likeneſs of thoſe men whom you fancy to be in Heaven: He forbids you <hi>to Bow down to them,</hi> and yet you Kneel to them: He forbids you <hi>to Serve them,</hi> and behold all your Prieſts are employed in their Service and Worſhip, one ſaith Maſs, another ſmoaks the Idol's noſtrils with Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fumes, another reads unto him his Goſpel, another is buſie to light Wax-candles about him, all the reſt are ſinging his Praiſes. What think ye, <hi>Papiſts!</hi> will not God, that declares himſelf to be a jealous God, be offended to ſee you pay unto ſuch ſenfleſs Idols that Honour and Service which he hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly forbidden? Will not he puniſh you according to his threatning, <hi>to the third and fourth Generation?</hi> There is no perſon of the leaſt reaſon will have this thought, for the thing of it ſelf is very plain; we need not much Logick to diſcover this Errour, and to condemn it. Therefore it is not without good cauſe that the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> forbids the reading of the Holy Scripture, nouriſhes her people with
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:95424:35"/>a ſtrong and indiſputable reſpect for the Pope and his Oracles, although he commands things contrary to God's Word, they believe nevertheleſs that they are obliged to obey and credit whatſoever he ſaith as an Article of their Faith, and to curſe as Hereticks all ſuch as follow not their example. The Reaſons that they pretend to juſtify their Superſtitions are very fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous and unlikely: They commonly tell us, <hi>That they worſhip not the Image, nor the Saint that is thereby repreſented, but God in that Saint ſhewed unto us by the Image.</hi> This Reaſon is very impertinent, ſeeing that God forbids not only <hi>the worſhipping of Images,</hi> in the ſame manner as we believe the Heathens did, but he forbids us <hi>to make them,</hi> to make <hi>any likeneſs,</hi> to carry it abroad, <hi>to ſerve and fall upon our knees before it;</hi> which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> do daily. Beſides, this Reaſon hath no likelihood; for we ſee by our experience every day, that the Saint, or rather the Image of the Saint is worſhipped and reverenced, and not God in the Saint, as the <hi>Papiſts</hi> would fain perſwade us. For if they worſhip only God in the Saint, wherefore do they eſteem more a graven Image than a painted one? We can never ſee the people going out of their Pariſhes and Precincts to pay their homages to an Image painted in another place; wherefore is this? If they only ſeek in the Image the reſemblance of the Saint, to call to their minds his virtuous beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour and actions; wherefore do the <hi>Papiſts</hi> beyond the Seas trot a-foot an hundred leagues from their own homes, to cringe and bow to a monſtrous Image, which in ſome places hath not the appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of a man, who ſhould be repreſented decently,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:95424:36"/>about ſix foot high; for this Image is like a miſhapen Dwarf, ugly and ill-favoured, having the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> ſtanding by him in the ſhape of a Onild about ſeven or eight years of age; whereas theſe perſons leave their own Pariſh-Churches, next to their houſes, where the Image of the ſame Saint more decent, more like to the Original? and more beautiful, ſtands without receiving the like reſpect. Wherefore do we ſee in the Church of St. <hi>Anna</hi> of <hi>Auray,</hi> in <hi>Britany,</hi> fifty or ſixty thouſand Pilgrims in her Feſtival-day, whereas it may be not ten ſhall be found in other Chappels dedicated to the ſame Saint, at that time? Wherefore is there ſuch a vaſt number of ſilver and golden arms, legs, hearts, heads, and little children hanging there, rather than in the other Churches conſecrated to the ſame Saint? where, it may be, we ſhall find no other Ornaments but thoſe which have been dedicated to, and left her by the devout Snails behind them; I mean, their ſilver-colour'd ſlime with which they beautifie her walls, and paint the face of this worthy Saint; it may be we ſhall find there nothing but a crazy Shrine, broken in many places, and one before the great Altar made up with the tayl of ſome old Gown, and ſo tatter'd, that many times it is no eaſie task to tell of what ſtuff and colour it was of, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Wherefore do the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon people throng to this Church only, their hands loaden with Croſſes, Beads, Medals, and other bau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, to have them touch the Image of St. <hi>Ann,</hi> which to my knowledge is but a block of decayed wood, almoſt rotten, and which was found in a puddle, lying in the mud over head and ears; if they believe not
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:95424:36"/>in this wood any divine virtue more than ordinary, and more than in other Images of this Saint? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore have the <hi>Carmelits,</hi> the Keepers of this Church, been ſo careful to preſerve ſo long every morſel and crum of this rotten wood which they have been for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to cut off to mend the Image? and wherefore have they offered it about the Countrey in little bits to the Noble perſons and Gentry, that have deſired it to ſanctifie their Cloſets, if they did not believe in this crazy wood ſome holy quality, ſome wonderful vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue, like to that which the Heathens affirmed to be in their Idols? Let them not therefore tell us that they ſeek nothing elſe in the Image of a Saint but the repreſentation and likeneſs, to call their Virtues to remembrance. For they take all men to be fools and Idiots, whom they would perſwade to admit of this excuſe, by doing what they do. A Heathen might with as much reaſon tell us that he is a Chriſtian, that he believes, and that he acknowledgeth and and worſhippeth but one only God; when I ſee him upon his knees before his Idols, offering to them his perfumes.</p>
               <p>To ſay the truth, I think that there is but little difference between the ancient <hi>Heathens</hi> and the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>Papiſts;</hi> if there be any, it is only in their names; for at preſent the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſpeak in the ſame Idolatrous language as the <hi>Heathens</hi> did, for without exception nor reſervation, they ſay now in the Popiſh Dominions that the Images themſelves may be worſhipped; I am certain that the <hi>Heathens</hi> never ſhewed more reſpect to their Gods, than the <hi>Papists</hi> do at preſent to their Images. This thought came into my mind at every
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:95424:37"/>time that I did look over the Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtories where they mention the <hi>Pagans</hi> Idolatries. I was confirmed in it by what one of the moſt famous of the Popiſh Doctors tells us; <hi>Thomas Aquinas,</hi> named by them the Angelical Doctor, maintains very ſolidly and rationally, that a man or a child that hath at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained to an age able to underſtand the natural truths, and to make uſe of his reaſon, if he can but diſcourſe upon the things that he ſees, he muſt needs diſcover the neceſſity of a firſt Being, of a primitive Principle, the Origin of all other things; of a firſt Truth, the only ſource of the reſt; of a firſt Cauſe, that gives motion and action to all ſecondary cauſes; he muſt needs find the neceſſity of the Being of a Sovereign Moderator and Governour of the Univerſe, who commands in chief over all things that are and ſhall be in the World: It is not poſſible but that ſuch an one muſt find out by the light of Nature, that <hi>There is One God, and that there can be bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> one Only God.</hi> When I had made this ſuppoſition, and did nevertheleſs find that <hi>Ariſtotle, Plato, Pythagoras, Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſian, Trajan,</hi> and other Emperors until the time of <hi>Conſtantin</hi> the Great, had Canonized many men, and reared up unto them publick Statues, to receive the Worſhip of the People, and Sacrifices; and that a certain <hi>Valentin</hi> had cauſed no leſs than thirty to be made of a new faſhion, fifteen makes and fifteen fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males. Is it poſſible, ſaid I to my ſelf, that men ſhould be ſo ſtupid as not to underſtand that there can be but one only God, one only true, perfect and ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Divinity? Had not they as well as we, the light of Reaſon and Nature to know this? Yes, doubtleſs
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:95424:37"/>they Knew it, and according to the judgment of <hi>Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Aquinas,</hi> it was unpoſſible but that they muſt have this diſcovery; they knew this God, they did worſhip him, they did rear unto him Altars as well as to the other Gods: As may appear by that Altar at <hi>Athens,</hi> conſecrated to the <hi>Unknown God,</hi> which was the occaſion of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Preaching unto them: ſome of theſe primitive Heathens did place Jeſus Chriſt in the number of their Gods. How came they there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to be guilty of Idolatry? wherefore are they accuſed of this crime? It was becauſe they did wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip men and other creatures with the true God. They did fancy ſome divine qualities in certain crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, and therefore they reverenced them, or rather they reverenced and adored God in them: For we cannot conceive how thoſe great Philoſophers, who are yet received amongſt us as our Teachers, could worſhip a Rat as a true God; it is not credible that they were guilty of ſo great a miſtake, to take a Rat or an Onion for the great Creator of Heaven and Earth. Neither did they imagin that their <hi>Caeſars</hi> and their <hi>Hero's,</hi> men whom they had ſeen entring into the world, living and departing as other men, were real Gods; but they believed that they were the chief Friends and Favourites of the true God. They had ſeen them perform notable and wonderful deeds whiles they were on earth, which made them judge that God had yet a particular affection for them, and that he had more regard of them than of other men; therefore they thought themſelves obliged in duty to pay unto them more reſpect, to adore in them the divine qualities which God had given them,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:95424:38"/>and to pray unto them, as to perſons whom they imagined to have an influence upon God, and to be well eſteemed of him. For this cauſe they built for them Temples, reared up Altars, erected their Images, and put them in frequented places, to be there adored of the people; they appointed Feſtivals, that they might be then worſhipped in a particular manner; in theſe ſolemn days the people did throng together to kneel before theſe dumb Statues, to offer to them their Vows, Prayers, and Sacrifices; all which are homages due to none but to God alone. This was their fault, this was their crime, which cauſeth them to be condemned of Idolatry. Don't we, ſaid I to my ſelf, don't we do the ſame as they did<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> do not we render to our Saints and Images the ſame devotion as the Heathens did to their falſe Gods? Let us judg by this compariſon between them and us. They made Images, we do the like; they ſet them in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick places, we likewiſe; they did fall down and kneel before them, and burn incenſe unto them, and do not we do the ſame? they prayed unto them in their need, to <hi>Mars</hi> in time of War, to <hi>Neptune</hi> when they did ſet ſayl to go to Sea, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Don't we <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſaid I, imitate them? Theſe and ſuch like conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations did often trouble land diſturb me againſt my will, for I could not well ſuffer ſuch reflexions that did lay open to me the nakedneſs and abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations of my Religion, ſo much like to the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theniſh, condemned by God himſelf. For the <hi>Papiſts</hi> in time of War fly to the Saints that are the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors of their Kingdoms; as if St. <hi>Denis,</hi> St. <hi>Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> and the other Protectors of <hi>France</hi> were at their
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:95424:38"/>requeſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gage in a quarrel for their ſakes in the Court of Heaven, againſt St. <hi>James</hi> St. <hi>Thereſia,</hi> and the other Protectors of <hi>Spain</hi> when thoſe two Nations are at variance. The <hi>Papists</hi> pray to St. <hi>Yues</hi> when they are at Law, becauſe he was a very good Lawyer; as if ſuch as were of an employment on Earth were to continue it in Heaven; St. <hi>Joſeph</hi> was a Carpenter, St. <hi>Criſpin</hi> a Shooemaker, and ſo of the reſt. We call upon St. <hi>Roch</hi> in time of the Plague, St. <hi>Eutropius</hi> for the Dropſie, becauſe the Legend informs us that theſe Saints have been ſick of thoſe Diſeaſes; as if the Saint that hath been troubled with an infirmity on Earth, did enter into Paradiſe only to become there the Phyſician of it, to get a Patent, and paſs the degree of Doctor. They pray to the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi> at all times and ſeaſons, and give her many ridiculous names; they pray to her for their Eye-ſight, ſtiling her <hi>Lady of the Light;</hi> they worſhip her by the name of <hi>Our Lady of good News,</hi> when they have any Ships ſayling upon the Seas; they call upon her in diſtreſs and affliction, and ſtile her <hi>Our Lady of Gladneſs;</hi> in a grievous Sickneſs they make their addreſſes to her, and flatter her with this title, <hi>Our Lady of Pity,</hi> or, <hi>Our Merciful Lady;</hi> and in all other neceſſities they honour her with theſe glorious Names, <hi>Our Helpful Lady, Our Aſſisting Lady, Our Lady adorned with all kind of Virtues:</hi> Thus to this one Saint they aſcribe many names, titles and properties, that they might make the ſilly people believe that ſhe is in ſome reſpect not much unlike unto God, whoſe attributes and perfections are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit. But that which I find to be very ridiculous
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:95424:39"/>amongſt them, is the manner of repreſenting and worſhipping Jeſus Chriſt: they have made him a monſtrous Statue, about ten or twelve foot high, which they baptize by the name of St. <hi>Saviour;</hi> now this Saint, diſtinguiſhable from their other petty Saints by his great ſtature and large bulk, is wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped by them for the preſervation of Corn, and of the Vines from the cold and froſt, for the curing of their Cows of a diſeaſe called the <hi>Swelling,</hi> and for the healing of the Horſes of the diſtemper named the <hi>Staggers;</hi> this Saint is prayed to for to keep their Sheep from the <hi>Rot,</hi> their Bees from dying, and their Lambs from the fury of the Wolves, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Therefore on his Feſtival-day at <hi>Nantes</hi> and at <hi>Tours,</hi> and other places where theſe great Images are erected, you might ſee an infinit number of Pilgrims of all ages, conditions and eſtates, bringing their gifts to theſe Statues; one brings thred, another wool, this man corn, another butter, and ſome, ſucking pigs or pieces of bacon, others bring grapes or pots of honey, or other commodities, but all bring wax-tapers to burn all the while that Maſs is ſaying at his Altar, all come with money or ſome other thing; ſo that about the Altar of this good Saint at ſuch a Solemnity you may find coffers full of wheat, barrels filled up with butter, tables loaden with great pieces of meat, and ſuch a prodigious number of little wax candles, that one time when I had the charge to gather up the remains, which the people did caſt yet lighted at the foot of the Statue, although each end of the candle was ſo ſhort that I could not hold it in my hand any longer, I gathered up in five hours full threeſcore and
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:95424:39"/>ten pounds of wax. It may be that ſome ingenious <hi>Papists</hi> will turn all this to the advantage of their Church, as they do the other abuſes and abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions committed in it: They will ſay, that this is an expreſſion of the wonderful Faith of their people, therefore they are apt to blame a Religion where they cannot ſpy ſo much Zeal amongſt the Profeſſors, and accuſe it, as if ſhe had neither Faith nor Devotion: But we may very well ſuffer them to ſpeak in their own defence, for this is a moſt palpable Idolatry, the Heathens were never guilty of ſo much; I do not think that it is poſſible to do more to Jeſus Chriſt if he did return into the world. But I may ſay they are to be excuſed, if they entertain their people in theſe Idolatries for a thouſand Crowns, which they receive in one day by the credit of one of theſe Ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, may ſatisfie for a mortal Sin, and free them from the penalty that it deſerves.</p>
               <p>There is but one thing more required to make them perfectly like to the Heatheniſh Idolaters, which is to have an univerſal Idol, proper to repreſent ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Saints, which might ſerve in many Feſtivals. The Emperor <hi>Trajan</hi> had an Idol of this nature; he had a golden head of an Idol kept ſecretly in his Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet, which he cauſed to be put upon the body of the Statues that he had a mind to worſhip; in this manner he did take off the head of his Gods as he thought fitting. I have ſeen amongſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſomething like to this, in a little Town of <hi>Britany,</hi> in the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick of <hi>Vannes;</hi> if it were not for the reſpect that I bear to ſome perſons concerned, I would name all the circumſtances, which I ſhall be forced to do, and
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:95424:40"/>many other things that I now conceal, I ſhall declare to the World, if any offers to accuſe me of lying and falſhood: in that place I have ſeen a mutable Saint carried up and down, wearing ſeveral apparels, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the peoples devotion; it was the Image of St. <hi>Maurice,</hi> who was prayed unto in his day, that he might heal the ſucking Babes of a diſeaſe called by the Countrey-people <hi>Carrel,</hi> a benumming diſeaſe, or the Rickets. On St. <hi>Giles</hi>'s day they carried the Image to another place, and of a Biſhop that it was before they made it an Abbot, cloathing it accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and ſeeking unto it for another diſtemper called the Diſeaſe of St. <hi>Giles.</hi> On St. <hi>Yves</hi>'s day they chang'd his Abbot's attire into that of a Lawyer, they put a corner-cap upon the Image's head, and a bag full of Writings in its hand inſtead of a Croche; in this manner it continued to be St. <hi>Yves</hi> until another Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtival-day; and the people did pray unto it not only to get the better of their Suits in Law, but alſo that St. <hi>Yves</hi> might kill and deſtroy ſuch as were thought to be the authors and inventers of calumnies caſt upon them. For the <hi>Papists</hi> there, when they are injured by any ſlanderous diſcourſe, or by another, they ſummon the ſuppoſed offendor to appear before St. <hi>Yves</hi> within a year; for they confidently believe that he that hath done the wrong ſhall ſurely dye be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the limited time: Let any man judge, if it be likely that a Saint ſhould deſtroy a man for a trifle. We may from hence perceive what grievous abuſes, errors, ſuperſtitions and miſtakes reign in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> There is therefore no difference between this Church and the Heathens. I relate not here the
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:95424:40"/>follies and abominations that have been heretofore practiſed, but theſe that are now viſible; I intend not to recollect the paſſages of the time paſt, but only to make mention of the preſent; I ſpeak not by hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay, but that which I have often ſeen to my unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able grief and confuſion; becauſe I was in reaſon forced to condemn a Religion which I was engaged to ſupport and maintain, and to preach up a Worſhip which I knew in my ſoul to be pure Idolatry.</p>
               <p>I did often wiſh, that the <hi>Papiſts</hi> would but confine themſelves to the limits of Reaſon in their Zeal and Devotion for theſe petty Saints; and would have ſhewn more to St. <hi>Peter,</hi> St. <hi>Paul,</hi> or to the other Apoſtles, but they are not ſo much eſteemed, becauſe they are not in ſuch reputation for their Miracles; I did often obſerve their Churches forlorn, their Images without ornaments, all covered with duſt, and the Spiders hanging by their lips and noſes; I did not ſee ſo many ſacks full of wax, ſo many arms, legs, dugs of ſilver and of gold, crutches, hoods, ſhirts, and garments of little Children hung up in their Chappels, as are round about the Churches of theſe Saints ſo much in vogue for their pretended Miracles: The Feſtivals of thoſe great Saints unto whom we are next unto Chriſt moſt obliged for our Religion, are celebrated with little or no ſolemnity; there are no more Chappels built for their ſakes, and ſuch as are erected are decaying every day; they are put out of their places, and grow out of credit, and other new Saints put in, as I took notice; their Images are caſt behind the Church doors amongſt the ſweepings, and lie along with the beſoms, becauſe they cannot
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:95424:41"/>get their expences, their Chappels and Altars coſt more to keep them, than they bring profit; whereas if it be but generally credited that the rotten. Image of a little Saint hath been pull'd out of the dirt and mire, that ſuch a one grants every man his requeſt, that he obtains for them their ſuits in Law, that he procures a ſafe arrival to Ships and Merchants goods at Sea, that he gives rain or fair weather as people require, that he heals diſeaſes, the Tooth-ach, the infirmities of the Eyes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> all the world will throng to him, all will run with their hands full of Gifts, and laden with ſtately Offerings. From whence proceeds this? It is becauſe that people have forſaken God, to adhere to the creature, and their minds are poſſeſſed with a deviliſh ſuperſtition, which aims ſo much at their preſent advantage, that they will have no devotion but for themſelves, they will ſeek nothing but their own contentment in the worſhip of their God, nor adore him but for their profits.</p>
               <p>What I have heard from the mouth of a Suffragan of a Biſhop of <hi>Britany,</hi> whoſe name I ſhall conceal for the reſpect I have for him, will further confirm unto you this Truth: He aſſured me, that when he was in the Viſitation with his Biſhop, he paſſed by a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh ſituate at the entrance of a Foreſt, where the Countrey people did worſhip a Saint named St. <hi>Gon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tran,</hi> or <hi>Gautran,</hi> that he might protect their Sheep from the Wolves; the Biſhop's curioſity more than his devotion led him into the Pariſh-Church, to ſee the Saint, whom he found holding a Wolf tyed to his garment, but ſo much decayed, that there was ſcarce any thing to be ſeen of the Saint, only the bold
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:95424:41"/>Wolf did there appear: the Biſhop being a good and underſtanding man, and ſuch a one as labours to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move and baniſh away, as much as he can, all Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitions of this kind, commanded the Image to be taken down, with the Wolf, and to be burnt together; becauſe the Saint being decayed by degrees, and va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing out of ſight, the Country-people began to reverence, and pay their devotions to the Wolf: If the reſt of the <hi>Roman</hi> Biſhops were but like to this Prelat, the Popiſh Religion would ſoon become Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med. Now it happened by chance that the very day that this Protector of the flocks was conſumed in the fire, the Wolves of the Foreſt came out and carried away three Sheep out of the Village; the people im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately believed that the Saint had ſent them this misfortune, becauſe he had been burned in the flames; therefore they flocked about the Suffragan, whom they believed to be the occaſion of the Saint's burning, they loaded him with imprecations and curſes, and threatned him in ſuch a manner, that if he had not withdrawn himſelf out of their ſight, they had ſtoned him. All this makes me believe, that theſe <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſeek not ſo much God's honour, and the glory of their Saints, as their own worldly gains and benefit, as the Heathens did when they worſhipped their Idols: For I am fully perſwaded, that if the Saint that is reverenced in the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> were a Devil, they would nevertheleſs pay him reſpect and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, if he had but the reputation of working Mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles and granting Petitions, ſo abominable they are in their Superſtitions.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:95424:42"/>§ There is another grievous abuſe crept in, occaſioned by the Relicks of the Saints, becauſe the Primitive Chriſtians did entomb with honour, and ſecure the bodies of the deceaſed Martyrs, and gather up the aſhes and bones of their conſumed bodies, that the Heathens might not expreſs their cruelty upon them after death, nor make a ſport of them after death; therefore by degrees this ſuperſtition is crept in: men pay them now as much reſpect as to Chriſt's body, if it were upon earth. This Idolatry was in St. <hi>Auſtin</hi>'s days, as he himſelf declares, <hi>de opere Monach. c.</hi> 2. <hi>The Devil hath cloathed a great many of his hypocrites with a Monkiſh attire, they wander up and down the Provinces without being ſent; they are never ſetled, never fixed, never reſting; ſome of them,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>make ſale of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs members, or ſuch as are ſuppoſed to be ſo, &amp;c.</hi> This Traffick is nothing in compariſon of that which is now-a-days; for ſuch things are ſold at an exceſſive rate, as dear as the Devil intended to buy Chriſt, <hi>with the power of Kingdoms and their glory,</hi> upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition <hi>to fall down to them, and worſhip them;</hi> the whole World is full of this deceitful commodity, which may be ſaid to be the moſt ſubject to cozenage. We have good cauſe to wonder, to hear no leſs than eight or ten Churches boaſting to have the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi>'s Girdle, Chriſt's Winding-ſheet and Seamleſs-coat; there have been many ſuits in Law in the Courts of Parliament between ſeveral Churches, about the keeping of one Relick, for every one did affirm theirs
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:95424:42"/>to be the trueſt. If all the bits of wood which are now eſteem'd to be pieces of our Saviour's Croſs, were gather'd in a heap, one hundred men would not be ſufficient to carry them; and if all the nails which are ſaid to be the true nails of his Croſs were toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, there would be enough to nail a Coach: we may ſay the ſame of all the other Inſtruments of his Paſſion; I would mention them all, but they are already reckoned up by others; and there is no man that hath peep'd out of his Cradle, and ſeen never ſo little of the World, but knows what I ſay to be true. Go to <hi>Turin,</hi> there you ſhall find ſome ready to ſwear that Chriſt's Winding-ſheet is there kept entire; go to <hi>Beſançon,</hi> you ſhall find the ſame thing. But that which hath ſurprized me moſt, was that which I have ſeen in a Convent of devout Virgins unto whom I was a long time Confeſſor. I had no deſign to name them; but becauſe ſome have accuſed me of falſhood in this Article, I find my ſelf forced againſt my will to particularize more than I intended: it was in the Nunnery of Religious <hi>Carmelits</hi> called of <hi>Naza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth,</hi> in the City of <hi>Vennes,</hi> in the Province of <hi>Britany.</hi> At a certain time I went in amongſt theſe devout Nuns, to receive the Confeſſion of one of them upon her death-bed, when I came a way, three or four of them according to their cuſtom brought me back from the place where their ſick are kept, to the gate; one of them invited me to viſit their ancient Chapter, which was an old decayed Chappel at a corner of their Convent: I went with them, and at the entrance I wondered to ſee them kneel in a place where I perceived no Image, I deſired them to tell
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:95424:43"/>me the cauſe; they informed me that it was becauſe of ſome Relicks that were there; I went to them, and found in the Wall, in a place very clean, a great number of Bones, with an Inſcription that declared that they were the Relicks of eleven thouſand Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins. I asked of them the reaſon why they had not put them into a veſſel fit for Relicks, according to the cuſtom, and why they did not make them more pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick? They replied, that the Biſhop had cauſed them to be viſited before he would ſuffer them, by three Chirurgeons and the Phyſician of the Convent, and that all of them had found and agreed together, that the moſt part of theſe Relicks were the Bones of Horſes; nevertheleſs they were reſolved not to burn them, as they had been adviſed, becauſe their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Records did aſſuredly tell them that they were the Bones of theſe marcyred Virgins; they did fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay that it was poſſible in the maſſacre of theſe Virgins, that there might be an Horſe killed amongſt them, this did not make the reſt leſs true and real Relicks. I anſwered them, It may be that the Bones of ſome of thoſe cruel Butchers were killed by the Soldiers that guarded them, were there alſo; it is not therefore well done, ſaid I, to kneel to them: one of them anſwered, You preach to us every day that we are ſaved by Faith. This is the uſual anſwer which they return every time that ſuch like miſtakes are objected to them: As if Faith, that looks upon God as its only object, or upon the divine enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, had need of the Bones of a dead Horſe to aſſiſt its contemplation, as if it did require from us a veneration for the Relicks of a dead Beaſt, or of an
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:95424:43"/>Idolater. Let any man, that queſtions the truth of what I ſay, inquire, or cauſe to be inquired, from the Nuns of that Convent, I am certain that they will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm this relation. From that time I took away all the Relicks that I had carefully kept, and gave them to friends, putting in their room another, which was worth a great deal more than the former, of which I was then more certain.</p>
               <p>For in regard that men go in pilgrimage two or three hundred leagues, to look upon our Saviours winding ſheet, the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi>'s peruque, St. <hi>John Baptist</hi>'s head, and other Relicks, I did conceive that I could find one nearer that was worth all theſe: It was the piece of linnen which is called the <hi>Corporal,</hi> upon which we put the chalice and the conſecrated bread in the Maſs: I took a piece of it, upon which I had oft-times placed the conſecrated wafer, for it was old and decayed. This hath been done by many be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides my ſelf. If my Doctrine and Religion be true, ſaid I, this is a good as Chriſt's winding ſheet, as His ſeamleſs coat, the pillar, and the holy Croſs, the crown of thorns, the handkerchief of St. <hi>Veronica,</hi> and the other Relicks, which receive ſo many pilgrimages from far. All their ſanctity is derived from the Body of Jeſus Chriſt, which they have had the honour to touch. Beſides we are not certain if they be true, for there are ſo many Churches that quarrel about them, that we have cauſe to doubt; but I am certain ſaid I, according to my belief, that this linnen hath touch'd the Body of Jeſus Chriſt. This linnen there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I laid up ſafe in my box of Relicks, where I kept it along while after. I am perſwaded I had good rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to do ſo, in regard of the nature of the thing,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:95424:44"/>and aſſurance that I had I think that every good <hi>Roman Catholick</hi> ought to do the ſame, if he hath any belief in his Religion and Doctrine; for if their exceſſive faith, which they have for Relicks, is pleaſing to God, and ſufficient to cauſe Miracles to be done by them, although theſe relicks be falſe, as they themſelves confeſs to happen ſometimes; what is the reaſon that their Religion doth not cauſe them to repoſe their truſt in that which they believe to have certainly touch'd the Body of Jeſus Chriſt? and wherefore doth not this linnen produce Miracles? Nevertheleſs we ſee that ſcarce any body reſpects it, 'tis caſt aſide with other linnen without reſpect; a little bit of St. <hi>Francis</hi>'s ſlipper is more reverenced than all ſuch linnen and chalices of the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Wherefore do we not ſee their Zealots gather up the parings of their Prieſts nails, that touch their God every day? It is certainly becauſe they have no faith where they ſhould have; or if they have, it is but an erroneous faith, that is not able to work a Miracle: It hath not that efficacy as their belief, or their miſtaking of a ſhip nail for one of our Saviour's Croſs, and the bones of an horſe for that of ſhe Saints, as the <hi>Vapiſts</hi> would perſwade. They may reply, that the linnen, the chalice, and the Prieſts nails, have touched only the elements: But I anſwer, are not theſe elements ſtrictly united to the Body of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt? This is the reaſon they pretend for their adoring them. Their Divines declare this union ſo ſtrict and extraordinary, that they make no difficulty to compare it to the Hypoſtatical Union, for as they ſay both are divine and wonderful; for as the humanity ſubſiſts in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carnation, without a natural and a proper ſubſiſtence,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:95424:44"/>likewiſe the bread and the wine remain in this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, without their own and natural ſubſiſtency, which they ſuppoſe to be deſtroyed, to give way to a Tranſubſtantiation. Theſe things being ſo, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore may not the elements ſanctifie a thing, ſeeing that they are really united to Jeſus Chriſt, God-Man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and why do the <hi>Papiſts</hi> ſo little regard that thoſe things that are known to have touch'd them, when they reverence others that are ſaid, without any like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood of truth, to have approached near to Chriſt's humanity? This is unjuſt, and a reproach to their Faith, not only in regard of Relicks, but alſo in regard of their Sacrament of the Altar.</p>
               <p>§. Let us proceed next to another Article of the Popiſh Faith. That whoſoever depends not upon the Pope, whoſoever don't acknowledge him for their Lord, and the Head of the Church; whoſoever he be that lives out of his obedience, ſhall be infallibly damned: of which Article I could never be fully perſwaded; therefore I was always very favourable in enjoyning penances to them that did willingly in their Confeſſions diſcover that they doubted of the truth of this part of the Popiſh Creed: For ſuch as behold the manner of the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> living, and their Chriſtian behaviour, cannot well be perſwaded of it; I have known ſome Ladies miſerably tormented with deſpair, becauſe they could not be perſwaded of the damnation of ſuch perſons: My ghoſtly Father, have they ſaid to me, I am damned, and without hopes of ſalvation, for I cannot poſſibly believe one of the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:95424:45"/>Articles of our Creed: I cannot be perſwaded that ſuch a Lady, a <hi>Hugonot,</hi> can be damned, in regard ſhe is ſo pious and virtuous in her converſation; every morning I know that ſhe is about an hour at her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votions in her cloſet, afterwards ſhe takes a religious book and reads, or applies her ſelf to work, ſhe is never idle, all her diſcourſe is of God's holy Word, and her ſelf appears ſo ſenſible of what ſhe ſpeaks, that ſhe forceth tears from the eyes of the aſſiſtants; it is not poſſible to be more juſt, charitable, and fearing God than ſhe is; it is not poſſible to be more zealous in God's ſervice, and more careful to oblige her do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſticks to live well, according to the Laws of God; I cannot believe that ſuch a perſon can be damned: nor I neither, ſaid I to my ſelf, I am of your mind, nevertheleſs it was then my intereſt to diſſemble the inward perſwaſion of my mind; Don't let that trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble you, I was about to ſay to ſuch, if you have not committed a more grievous ſin than that, I ſhall not load you with an heavy penance. I am certain that many are of my mind in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> It is a cheat and a deſign, to force people to believe it as confidently as the moſt holy myſteries, and a great error, to tell them that they cannot have any hopes of ſalvation, if they are not perſwaded that the others are aſſuredly damned, although God commands us to the contrary by his Apoſtle <hi>not to judge others, Rom.</hi> 14.3. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.12. and aſſures us in his Goſpel, that there needs nothing elſe to attain unto ſalvation, <hi>but the keeping of his Commandments;</hi> which the <hi>Protestants</hi> profeſs to do, and perform. Therefore I did often argue in this manner: It is not poſſible to be damned without ſin, for ſin is that alone that ſhuts heaven,
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:95424:45"/>and draws upon us the wrath of God: Now there is no ſin but is againſt his commandments; either we muſt omit what he enjoyns, or commit what he forbids. Every one therefore that believes what God hath revealed unto us by his Prophets and Apoſtles, and by Chriſt, and ſhall keep the commandments of God, ſhall infallibly be ſaved: the Scripture declares it; <hi>He that believeth in me, although he were dead yet ſhall he live,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Joh.</hi> 11.25. <hi>and whoſoever liveth and believeth in me, ſhall never dye.</hi> He don't tell us <hi>we muſt believe in the Pope,</hi> to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved; but we muſt <hi>believe in him.</hi> He repeats theſe words in ſeveral paſſages of the Goſpel, <hi>Verily verily I ſay unto you, if any man keep my word he ſhall never ſee death:</hi> he ſpeaks the ſame to that man which en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of him what he was to do to be ſaved, <hi>If thou wilt enter into life, keep the commandments,</hi> Matth. 29.16. when he enquired which? Chriſt anſwered, <hi>Thou ſhalt not kill, thou ſhalt not commit adultery, thou ſhalt not steal, &amp;c.</hi> Now the <hi>Protestants</hi> profeſs and obſerve theſe two things; to believe in God, and to obey his commandments. This is their Faith, and the principles of their Religion; to believe all that God hath revealed, and to do all that he hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded. Wherefore ſhould they be damned? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they don't believe in the Pope, anſwers a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist,</hi> and becauſe they don't keep the commandments of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> But, my friend, from whence haſt thou that theſe two things are alſo neceſſary for thy ſalvation? is it from God, or from man? can you find in any paſſage of the Holy Scripture, or in the three Creeds of your Religion any thing of this doctrine? It is true, you ſhall find, <hi>I believe in God
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:95424:46"/>the Father Almighty, Creator of heaven and earth, and in Jeſus Christ his only Son our Lord,</hi> &amp;c. You ſhall not find there that you muſt believe in the Pope, that the Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> is the Head of all the Chriſtian Church, that he is infallible, and that he muſt be obeyed as God himſelf: You ſhall not find there any mention made of the Sacrifice of the Maſs, of Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatory, Indulgences, the Worſhipping of Images, nor of the other Articles of the Popiſh Religion. And the two other Creeds, made about two or three hundred years after the firſt, to explain and para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phraſe it, ſpeak of no ſuch things: Liſten atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively at your Morning Prayers, or when Maſs is ſung in your Churches publickly; you ſhall hear nothing of the Pope, nor of his Church, you ſhall only hear of the Articles which <hi>Protestants</hi> believe with leſs additions than you; for they credit them only becauſe God hath revealed them, they will have no mixture of humane authority with the divine. Look over all the commandments of God's Law, you ſhall not find there any thing of praying to Saints, of worſhipping of Images, of abſtinence from meats, of faſting in Lent, of confeſſion of ſins to men; but there you ſhall find that we muſt worſhip God, that we muſt not make any graven Image, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All theſe commandments are kept more religiouſly by the <hi>Protestants</hi> than by the <hi>Papists,</hi> what reaſon therefore can we find for their Damnation? how come they to be ſo bold as to thruſt this into their Creed as an Article of Faith; ambition and antichriſtian rage againſt them hath perſwaded them to it. But I wonder how they can offer to maintain this doctrine, with this addition, that there is no ſalvation but by
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:95424:46"/>an union with the Pope, whom they affirm to be the Head of the Church, and by conſequence, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence and give life to every one of its Members. Suppoſe the Pope is a wicked man, as many ſuch have been; according to their own confeſſion, if he be covetous, profane, lechrous, an Heretick, a Negro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mancer, or a helliſh Monſter, how can any relation and union with ſuch a one do me any good? can he make me partaker of that holineſs which he himſelf wants<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I have good cauſe to fear that he will infect me with his vices. Is it not a grievous miſtake, and a ridiculous fancy, to ſay, that I cannot pleaſe God, unleſs I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate with, and be related to his enemy; and that I muſt not expect ſalvation, but by a communion with him that is aſſuredly damned? Nevertheleſs this is one of the Articles of the Popiſh Creed and Faith.</p>
               <p>§. Their Doctrine concerning Traditions is alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Holy Word of God. It tends to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw us from our faith and belief in it. If Jeſus Chriſt did now live in the world, he might with reaſon treat the <hi>Papists</hi> in the ſame manner as he did the Phariſees: <hi>In vain do they honour me, teaching for doctrines the commandments of men; for laying aſide the commandment of God, ye hold the tradition of men, as the waſhing of pots and cups, and many other ſuch like things; you do tranſgreſs the commandment of God by your tradition: Mark</hi> 7.7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 13. <hi>Matth.</hi> 15.3. The moſt part of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> Principles and Articles of Faith are nothing but Doctrines and Commandments of men, which have altogether changed the appearance of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:95424:47"/>Chriſt's Church in all thoſe Kingdoms where they have been admitted. I might make this appear more plainly, if I did but run over all the grievous im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinencies, that are by this means received as ſo many Articles of Faith in the Church of <hi>Rome;</hi> if I did but make an enumeration, of all the falſe Miracles publiſhed for true; but I ſhould exceed the narrow limits preſcribed to my ſelf. I ſhall therefore confine my ſelf to one thing, that hath very much ſcandaliſed me in this Doctrine, it is the reaſon and expedient that they have to maintain it, which tends to the total ſubverſion of Chriſtian Religion, and to the deſtruction of Chriſt's Church. For to perſwade people the more that their Traditions are neceſſary, they exalt them above the Authority of the Holy Scriptures, and advance ſuch doctrines, and propoſe ſuch queſtions, as might make any man an Atheiſt that will hearken to them. How do you know, ſay they, that theſe Writings that bear <hi>Moſes</hi>'s name have been written by him? How do you know that St. <hi>Matthew,</hi> St. <hi>Mark,</hi> St. <hi>Mark,</hi> St. <hi>Luke,</hi> and St. <hi>John,</hi> are Authors of the Goſpel? that St. <hi>Paul,</hi> St. <hi>James,</hi> and St. <hi>Peter,</hi> have written the Epiſtles? unleſs it be by Tradition? Have you ſeen the firſt Originals of theſe Writings, that you credit ſo much? And if you did ſee them, who is it can affirm, that they were written by theſe great Apoſtles, that have been dead ſo long? unleſs you believe the men of our days, who have received what they affirm, either by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, or otherwiſe, from the <hi>hear-ſay</hi> of their Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers. This we name <hi>Tradition. Pighius</hi> argues in this manner, <hi>Hierarch. Eccleſ. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2. This was alſo my reaſon and argument, that I have often made
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:95424:47"/>uſe of; but when I had ſeriouſly examined its ſtrength, its veracity and deſign, I found it to be but weak, and tending to undermine the foundations of our Faith, of our Laws and Religion; for if I might have the liberty to propoſe ſuch queſtions, I might as well make others, which ſhall intangle them in as great a difficulty as theirs do us: How know you, may I ſay, that your Tradition is good and true? How do you know, that ſuch as affirm St. <hi>Peter</hi> to have been Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> ſpeak truth? How came you to be perſwaded that there is a Biſhop of <hi>Rome?</hi> have you ſeen him? How are you certain, that the Pardons and Indulgences that you receive came from him? that he hath confirmed them with his ſigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture? could not the perſons that have delivered them to you counterfeit his hand? May not an Atheiſt make uſe very well of this argument, and ask, How do you know that there is any other God beſides the Sun? have you ever ſeen him? have you ever ſpoken with him? How do you know that there are three Perſons in the Godhead? How do you know that Jeſus Chriſt hath lived upon earth? that there have been Apoſtles? <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This is the drift and end of theſe queſtions, which we muſt reject as the Devils cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to enſnare our Faith. <hi>Hearken not to thoſe that will ſpeak in this manner,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Austin, Confeſſ. l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>How knoweſt thou that theſe Books proceed, and are derived unto men from the Spirit of a true God? for this we must believe above all things.</hi> And <hi>Tertull. contra Hermogen. I acknowledge the fulneſs of the Scripture,</hi> Her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mogenes <hi>cannot find there any pretence for his errours, therefore he and his fellows flye to the aſſiſtance of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition.</hi> And elſewhere he ſaith, <hi>Take away from He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:95424:48"/>that which is common to them with the Heathens, and confine them to the Holy Scriptures, and they can no longer ſubſiſt. De Reſur. carnis.</hi> I think this anſwer is a ſufficient reply to the <hi>Papists.</hi> Many others have been given, which are to be read in the Books of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie. It is my judgment, that God hath fully as much power as men, and that his voice is as effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacious and perfect as ours. We are to be diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by our voices and ſpeeches, as when a Son hears his Fathers voice, he needs not that a Servant ſhould inform him that his Father ſpeaks; likewiſe our Saviour Chriſt aſſures us, that <hi>his ſheep hear his voice and know it.</hi> We need no other but Chriſt's voice to know that it is His, that He ſpeaks unto us in the Holy Scriptures. Let not the <hi>Papiſts</hi> propoſe any ſuch queſtions for the future, and let them take notice of what St. <hi>Jerome</hi> tells us upon <hi>Hagg. That the things that are invented are falſe, as for example, ſuch as are ſaid to be the Apoſtles traditions, which have no authority nor teſtimony from the Holy Scriptures, are mark'd by God's ſword.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. From this Doctrine of Tradition proceeds their Faith of Miracles, a Faith as ill grounded and ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous as the Traditions themſelves, that are but old wives tales. We may judge of ſuch as are related to us of former ages by them that are publiſhed and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in our days, of a thouſand there is ſcarce one that hath the leaſt appearance of reality, if we will but ſeriouſly conſider and examin them. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs they are as boldly delivered for truths in the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:95424:48"/>Popiſh Pulpits, as the Goſpel. I have declared many, being forced thereunto by my Office, that I knew to be very falſe. Several perſons of the common people have related to me accidents, that have happened in places of devotion, which they look'd upon as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Miracles; but when I have examined them well, I have underſtood that they were but natural effects. If they had addreſſed themſelves to ſome other per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, their belief and declarations had paſſed as cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant as Chriſt's Reſurrection from the dead, and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus</hi> riſing out of the Sepulchre; they had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded, and laid up for poſterity to read. For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample: A Country fellow comes to me, with two or three of his neighbours, aſſuring me, that his wife had been at the laſt gaſp, and that becauſe he had offered her to St. <hi>Mathurin</hi> or St. <hi>Anne,</hi> the very next day ſhe recovered of her diſtemper. But he did not tell me, that the Phyſitian, that had judged her ſickneſs ſo deſperate, was but a Country Chyrurgeon, who hath ſcarce ſeen the outſide of Phyſick Books, and therefore knew not how to judge of a diſeaſe by the ſymptoms. I have healed many in this manner, by preſcribing to them no other receipt but patience. I did not diſcover to them, that the dangerous diſtem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, which had taken from the Patient ſpeech, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from a <hi>Criſis,</hi> or the turning of the blood, or from the working of ſome violent phyſick. Another comes to me, and tells me, that his child hath been thought to be dead for ſeveral hours<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but when in time he comes to take notice, that it was a Convul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion-fit, or the Falling-ſickneſs, he don't go back to acquaint the Prieſt, that what he thought to be death is but a diſeaſe. Who is it that would not have
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:95424:49"/>really believed to be true, what the Biſhop of <hi>Angers</hi> publiſhed in print, he is a perſon not eaſily to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded; he cauſed an exact enquiry to be made, and was certainly informed that Jeſus Chriſt had viſibly appeared in the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Ulmes,</hi> in the Prieſts hands as he was ſaying Maſs? Yet he hath been forced to acknowledge, to the ſhame of the whole Church, that it was but a fiction of the Prieſt and a few Pariſhioners, who thought to enrich them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by that means: If this Prieſt had but dyed a few days after, he had been Canonized for a Saint; but he hath lived, and declared by his Life what manner of man he is: the Biſhop hath been forced for his ſcandalous behaviour to degrade him, and caſt him into a Priſon, where I think he remains yet. We may judge by this what to think of all the other Miracles noiſed abroad in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. The laſt Article relates to the Indulgences. I don't here queſtion whether the Pope hath power to par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don ſins when he pleaſeth; Jeſus Chriſt can do no more, the Phariſes would never allow him that power. I deſire therefore that the Divines of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> would reſolve me theſe Queſtions which I have often propoſed to my ſelf: Wherefore do the Popes proclaim their Univerſal Jubilees, which cauſes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o many thouſand people to trot to <hi>Rome;</hi> or to ſome other great City where the place is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, to gain them? For if they anſwer, that it is to obtain the forgiveneſs of our ſins: I may reply,
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:95424:49"/>that there is no need to go ſo far to obtain this for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs; there is no Pariſh but a full Indulgence may be bought every year ſeveral times: There is ſcarce a noted Town, but it may be purchaſed every day; only one being concerned and initiated into the Fraternity of the little habit of the Virgin, many times obtains for us above one hundred and fifty every year: I ſhall not ſpeak of the other means to get theſe priviledges and advantages. Now thoſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgences, as the Popiſh Divines affirm, free us as well from the puniſhment, as from the guilt of all manner of ſins: if therefore this is to be had in every Pariſh-Church, what need is there of a Pilgrimage to <hi>Rome?</hi> if all our ſins are pardoned, what will the Pope's or his Agents Abſolution profit us? Is not this to make a ſport of mens credulity, and to deal with them as with blind men and fools? It may be they will anſwer, that at ſuch ſolemn occaſions the Pope abſolves from grievous ſins, reſerved to himſelf, which are not forgiven every day; but if I have not been guilty of ſuch horrid crimes, wherefore am I ſollicited and preſs'd upon to go and purchaſe a Jubilee? wherefore am I obliged otherwiſe to make a general confeſſion of my ſins? and if I don't, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore am I look'd upon as an Atheiſt? From hence we might conclude that their Church is never perfect but in the time of the Jubilee, becauſe at that time only it hath a power to forgive all manner of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners: But Biſhops and Prieſts are to be found in every corner, that have power granted to abſolve theſe grievous and horrid ſins; there is ſcarce a petty Monk but will ſay he hath that priviledge, four or five ſins excepted, which ſcarce happen in an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:95424:50"/>years in a Province: If none but ſuch as are guilty of theſe ſins did go to <hi>Rome,</hi> the Roads of <hi>Italy</hi> would not be ſo populous as they are at this time.</p>
               <p>I might here mention the other Indulgences that may be obtained every day. The abuſes are ſo great and ridiculous, that if you pleaſe to view the inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of a Popiſh Zealot, you ſhall ſee ſtuff and trin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kets enough to ſet up a Shop: You ſhall ſee Beads of all ſizes, ſhapes and numbers, fifteen in a ſtring, fifty in another, thirty in another, ten in another; all this is full of myſtery: you ſhall ſee little garments, like childrens babies attire, ſome white, others red, others brown; you ſhall ſpy Medals of all ſorts, Cords with knots of ſeveral magnitudes, and Croſſes of all faſhions: The <hi>Papiſts</hi> are become ſo ridiculous to cauſe their Zealots to wear two pins a-croſs upon their ſleeve of breaſt, aſſuring them that they ſhall obtain the forgiveneſs of ſeveral days ſins, as often as they kiſs this Croſs, or pronounce over it two or three hard conjuring words. I was never more aſtoniſhed and ſcandalized than I was the laſt year, when I was ſent about the time of the Feſtival of the holy Sacrament to preach in the City where I made my abode, I found every body ſtored with theſe Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gences, wearing pins a-croſs, they inform'd me that the devout and right Reverend<note n="*">Theſe Knaves and Cheats of that bloody Society play a thouſand ſuch tricks in thoſe Kingdoms and Cities that are at their devotion, as in <hi>Spain, Italy</hi> and <hi>France.</hi>
                  </note> Father of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> called Father <hi>Huby,</hi> had recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded this notable piece of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion to them: By this means he diſpoſed of above ten mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions of pins; which he had the conſcience not to ſell, he gave them out of an exceſs of charity; but in
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:95424:50"/>requital his charity did require for every two pins a ſumm of money, to help his Brethren the <hi>Jeſuits</hi> travelling in <hi>China</hi> and in far Countries to ſay Maſs; for in thoſe places they cannot meet with ſuch fools that will encourage them, by contributing to their ſubſiſtence.</p>
               <p>If we did but run over all the other Tenents of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Faith, we ſhould find as many errours, miſtakes and abominations as we have done in theſe. But it is not my deſign to mention all, I intended to be more ſuccinct, and I look not upon my ſelf as able to make this deſcription ſo well as others who have more ſtudied the Diſputes and Controverſies.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>THE THIRD PART.</head>
               <p>THE Third Reaſon that hath ſo long kept me in the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion was grounded upon the practices and Laws of that Church, the ſolemn Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtivals, the Auricular Confeſſion, Abſtinence from Meats, the Forty days of Lent, the Prieſts Vows of Chaſtity, and the auſtere Lives of the Monks. All theſe things did preſent themſelves as it were in a body together in my mind, and cauſed me to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain ſo high an eſteem for Popery, where I ſaw ſo many holy and religious cuſtoms obſerved, that I could not look upon the reſt but with diſdain, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred and averſion, becauſe I could not find the ſame things.</p>
               <p>But when againſt my will I was forced to open my eyes, and being engaged by my Office to ſeek into the beginning of all the abominations that I ſaw acted in the world, I found that theſe things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:95424:51"/>from the Laws invented to deceive the moſt ſubtil wits, and intice the devouteſt ſouls into the broad road of hell, by the Devil, who ſometimes appears as an Angel of Light.</p>
               <p>§. What a vaſt number of diſorders have been occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by the many Feſtivals of the Church of <hi>Rome?</hi> There were ſo prodigious a multitude lately obſerved in <hi>France,</hi> that the King was forced about ſeven years ago to get a Diſpenſation for the eaſe and benefit of his People from the Pope, who aboliſhed a great many. But this Diſpenſation hath cauſed a ſtrange deformity in all the Biſhopricks of <hi>France:</hi> Some were willing to obey the Popes order, by caſting out of the Calendar ſuch Feſtivals as were aboliſhed; other Biſhops would not admit it; ſome cut off a few, kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping ſtill the reſt; others were offended, that the King did incroach upon their priviledges, therefore inſtead of diminiſhing the number of their Feſtivals, they eſtabliſhed new Feaſt-days; ſome faſt in the Saints Eve, and keep not the day; others regard nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the faſt nor the day; others cauſe them to be kept only 'till noon; others to prevent all inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niencies have appointed all Feaſt-days to be obſerved on the <hi>Sunday,</hi> and their Faſts on the <hi>Saturday:</hi> So that yet we may ſee two men of the ſame Village, or of the ſame Family, of a different perſwaſion; one obliged to keep a Feſtival-day for fear of a mortal ſin, and the other not; nay the ſame perſon is ingaged to this obſervation if he ſtays at home, but if he ſteps over a gutter or rivulet to go into another Pariſh he
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:95424:51"/>commits no ſuch ſin, and may do what he pleaſeth. Can any man think that theſe practices proceed from God? Yet this they believe, and the Caſuiſts amongſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> affirm.</p>
               <p>§. Auricular Confeſſion is another Invention of man's brain. The <hi>Romiſh</hi> Clergy have impoſed it out of policy, as a neceſſary means to keep men in their duty, and to hinder them from miſchievous at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempts. The deſign was good, but the means im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed is unjuſt and tyrannical: I may ſafely name it ſo without fear, for I know ſufficiently what I am to think and ſay upon this ſubject. I have read over and over the Holy Scriptures and the Fathers concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning this matter, and becauſe I did not truſt to my own judgment, I intreated the aſſiſtance of ſome Learned Men of my acquaintance, to ſee whether they could find any thing out of St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin,</hi> or other Fathers, to aſſiſt and confirm my Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, that I was to deliver in Sermons, which I compoſed upon this Subject; but I could never ſee nor find any paſſage there, that confirms this politick Inſtitution, as it is practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> We may find that we muſt confeſs our ſins unto God, but not to men; we may alſo find, that it is well done to declare and diſcover the troubles of our conſciences to them that have the rule over us, and are appointed by God to inſtruct us, that we may underſtand and receive from them ſeaſonable com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts and inſtructions. This is very uſeful to us, and ſometimes abſolutely neceſſary. But it is not required
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:95424:52"/>that we ſhould reveal all our weakneſſes, mention all our ſins ſmall and great, to particulariſe their num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber and quality, and all their circumſtances and ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravations, to a ſinful man, as vicious as my ſelf, who ought to confeſs alſo it may be to me, as the Prieſts of the ſame Church confeſs their ſins to one another; it is not required that I ſhould make this confeſſion, as it is practiſed with ſo many ridiculous queſtions, that teach us to commit ſins that we knew not before: The Caſuiſts are of opinion, that when a Prieſt ſhould be inclinable to the moſt abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minable ſins of lechery, and in danger to be tempted to them by every apprehenſion, yet when he receives the Confeſſion of a Virgin, he had better omit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing than to cauſe her to paſs over any thing, and to commit by this act a material ſin in their opinion: This can never be proved, unleſs the <hi>Papiſts</hi> offer to do it by a new Bible, by other Evangeliſts, and other Interpreters, than have yet written upon the Holy Scriptures.</p>
               <p>I could never digeſt the doctrine of the Popiſh Divines, that teacheth us two kind of ſorrows requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in true repentance; the one they name Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition, which is, ſay they, when we are grieved to have offended God for his ſake, becauſe he is ſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely good, and becauſe ſin diſpleaſeth him: this grief is ſufficient to obtain from God the forgiveneſs of our ſins, in caſe we cannot conveniently go to confeſs them; for if a Prieſt be preſent we cannot be diſpenſed from this duty. The other grief or ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, named Attrition, is when a man is grieved to have offended God out of worldly intereſt and ſelfiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, becauſe ſin deprives us of the hopes of Heaven,
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:95424:52"/>and condemns us to Hell, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> This ſorrow, ſay they, is not ſufficient of it ſelf to obtain the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of our ſins, but only when it is accompanied by the Prieſt's abſolution. That is to ſay, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though a man upon his death-bed ſhall confeſs all his ſins, if the Prieſt will be ſo hard-hearted to deny him abſolution, in caſe he departs in that eſtate with ſuch a ſorrow in his heart, he ſhall be damned for all that. Let any of the Popiſh Divines tell me which of the holy Evangeliſts have taught them this diſtinction? which of the Apoſtles did ever preach ſuch doctrine as this? Nevertheleſs I think they have reaſon to recommend it, becauſe the ſalvation or the damnation of ſouls is ſo highly concerned, according to their teaching, and many times of ten thouſand ſouls in one Church: This baſtard Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is not of the number of the Sacraments of which we are never to be partakers but once; for it is commanded every year at <hi>Eaſter,</hi> and ſome perſons are partakers of it almoſt every day, as is uſually practiſed in the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> What is the reaſon that neither Chriſt, nor his Apoſtles have ever mentioned it? Or rather how came theſe perſons to be ſo bold as to impoſe theſe diſtinctions as Articles of Faith? Is it poſſible that the Prieſt's preſence or abſence, or the opportunity of Confeſſion, makes our repentance true or falſe, according to ſuch trivial circumſtances? If I am at a diſtance from a <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſt, am I therefore to be look'd upon as if I were at as great a diſtance from God, and in a worſe eſtate than another from whoſe ſides the Prieſt is not to be drawn? Doth this cauſe my ſorrow to be leſs or more able to prevail upon God's mercy?
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:95424:53"/>Doth true repentance depend upon the Prieſt's good pleaſure? And Attrition, which is but an imperfect ſorrow, of no validity of it ſelf in God's ſight, is it more conſiderable, more perfect, and more able to ſave me, when a Prieſt ſhall have mark'd me with the ſign of the Croſs upon my forehead? when he ſhall have whiſpered two or three words in my ear? What am I the better for all this? Is God's Juſtice thereby ſatisfied? and his Mercy more inclinable to pardon me?</p>
               <p>According to this ridiculous Doctrine, ſuppoſe I ſhould weep and lament for my ſins as bitterly as St. <hi>Peter,</hi> with as many expreſſions of holy love as <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> if I do not confeſs them to a Prieſt, I ſhall be nevertheleſs damned for them. And ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe I ſhould be guilty of the moſt horrid crimes, if I can but imitate this imperfect ſorrow, a ſuperficial diſpleaſure to have offended God, for the love that I bear to my ſelf, if I reveal them to a Prieſt, I ſhall be ſaved notwithſtanding. Wretched <hi>Judas!</hi> hadſt thou had but a <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſt at the foot of thy Gibbet, thy Soul might have gone ſtreight to heaven; for he performed all the conditions required by the Popiſh Doctors in a true Penitent; for they ſay that three particulars are to be obſerved, the compunction or pricking of the heart, the confeſſion, and ſatisfaction; compunction in the ſoul, confeſſion of the mouth, and ſatisfaction of the hand. <hi>Judas</hi> was a zealous obſerver of theſe particulars, as may appear by his Hiſtory in the Goſpel, <hi>Matth.</hi> 27.4. He wanted not comp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nction, or a hearty diſpleaſure to have ſinned againſt God, for it is ſaid <hi>he repented:</hi> He confeſſed alſo his crime, <hi>I have ſinned,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>in betraying the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:95424:53"/>innocent blood. David,</hi> in his repentance, could ſay no more; and the greateſt Caſuiſts amongſt the <hi>Papiſts</hi> demand no more; for he did not confeſs only in ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral, but he mentions alſo the greatneſs and nature of his ſin. There was alſo in his repentance a ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, for he reſtored back his ill gotten money, <hi>he brought back the thirty pieces of ſilver.</hi> How comes it to paſs therefore, that penitent <hi>Judas</hi> was damned? It was, ſaith a <hi>Papiſt,</hi> becauſe there was no Prieſt at the foot of the Gibbet, where he hang'd himſelf, to give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> abſolution; if there had been one never ſo cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ptible, to ſpeak to him but theſe two words, <hi>Te abſolvo,</hi> he might have made him a Saint, and following Ages would have built Temples in honour of him, Altars and Images, as to the other Apoſtles, to receive the devotions of the People. Some may reply, that <hi>Judas</hi> had not that ſincere and hearty ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row required in a true Penitent, and that this was the cauſe of his damnation. I am of the ſame opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, I acknowledge that to be true; but I affirm, and can prove, that <hi>Judas</hi> had as much ſorrow and diſpleaſure as the <hi>Papists</hi> require in a ſinner, when they give abſolution, and aſſure him of his happineſs. I know that ſome of them will ſay, that this at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trition muſt be ſupernatural, grounded upon a divine faith, as the fear of forfeiting the joys of heaven, of falling into the pains and torments of hell, or a grief proceeding from theſe and ſuch like perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; it is not derived from God, or His Love, but from our intereſt revealed unto us by faith. In <hi>Judas,</hi> we may take notice of a diſpleaſure as great, and not much unlike to that which proceeds from theſe prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, as may appear by his own words, <hi>I have ſinned
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:95424:54"/>in betraying the innocent blood:</hi> He declares publickly the innocency of our Saviour, which was an act of faith; moreover he declares, that the conſideration of Chriſt's innocency was the chief cauſe of his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure. There is no ghoſtly Father of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> but will take <hi>Judas</hi>'s repentance, not only for an attrition, but alſo for a true contrition. I am certain that they give abſolution to many perſons, who never had ſo great a ſorrow for their ſins as <hi>Judas.</hi> Therefore why was <hi>Judas</hi> damned? St. <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> returns us a ſatisfactory anſwer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hich we may underſtand, how dangerous it is ſometimes to confeſs our ſins rather to men than to God: <hi>Arbitror,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>enim quod etiam Judas potuiſſet tanta Dei miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratione non excludi à venia, ſi poenitentiam, non apud Judaeos, ſed apud Chriſtum egiſſet.</hi> Ambr. l. 2. de poenit. c. 5. <hi>I am perſwaded,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>that</hi> Judas <hi>might have been admitted by God's infinite mercy, if inſtead of profeſſing his repentance to the</hi> Jews, <hi>he had addreſſed himſelf to Chriſt.</hi> He went to confeſs his ſin to the <hi>Jews,</hi> who inſtead of reproving him for it, and exhorting him to truſt in God's unſpeakable goodneſs, returned him an anſwer, that tended to confirm him in his malice, and caſt him into deſpair, <hi>Quid ad nos? tu videris;</hi> ſaid they to him; <hi>What is that to us? ſee thou to that.</hi> This is the true model of the <hi>Papiſts</hi> repentance: They confeſs their ſins to a Prieſt, as much loaden with guilt as they are themſelves. I have been drunk, ſaith a drunken Sot in his confeſſion to a ghoſtly Father, who is ſometimes more debauch'd: <hi>Quid ad nos?</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyes the Father, <hi>tu videris:</hi> It is no great crime, we are apt to be drawn away with the love of good company, therefore for penance I enjoyn thee to cauſe
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:95424:54"/>a Maſs to be ſaid for thee before the Virgin <hi>Mary</hi>'s Altar; after that he is perfectly abſolved. I have been guilty, ſaith another, twenty times of the ſin of Fornication; <hi>Quid ad nos?</hi> replies a lecherous Father-Confeſſor, <hi>tu videris.</hi> It is a difficult task to ſuppreſs the motions of love; therefore thou ſhalt for thy penance number over thy Beads, that is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for thee: ſuch a one is afterwards certain to obtain ſalvation, by this abſolution ſo eaſily obtained. I have worſhipped Images, will a nice conſcience it may be ſay, contrary to God's command; I have believed many things not agreeable to what is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded in the Holy Word of God; I have preferr'd man's inventions to the Laws of God, <hi>&amp;c. Quid ad nos? tu videris.</hi> Thou muſt do ſo, ſaith a Prieſt, by this means thou ſhalt come to be a Saint. This is a <hi>Judas</hi>'s repentance, and a dealing like to that of the <hi>Jews:</hi> Let any man judge if it be able to ſecure the ſalvation of our ſouls.</p>
               <p>I might add to this, that extraordinary Power which the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Prieſts claim of pardoning all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of ſins, and of blotting them out with the breath of two words. Is not this to make themſelves equal to Jeſus Chriſt, and to declare themſelves to be the Saviours of Man-kind? Wherefore do they treat their Penitents as ſlaves, and deal with them as if they were their Gods?</p>
               <p>Moreover, they treat the Son of God moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthily, and are guilty of the ſame ſin as the wicked <hi>Macedonians,</hi> who affirmed that the Holy Spirit was but the ſervant of the Father of Eternity. The <hi>Romiſh</hi> Divines deal with Chriſt in a more diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graceful manner: For by their doctrines they make
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:95424:55"/>him become their Prieſt's ſervant: For when they are pleaſed to ſay, we abſolve this ſinner, it is the ſame as if they ſaid to Jeſus Chriſt, we command thee to give to this ſoul ſanctifying grace, that it may be juſtified and acceptable to God the Father. We will not grant abſolution to that ſinner, that is to ſay, we forbid thee to ſhew him or her ſo much favour as thou didſt to penitent <hi>Mary Magdalen,</hi> to waſh away her ſins; this belongs to us; we will do it a fortnight hence; we command the ſinner to come to us at that time; until then we will bind him or her with a tye not to be looſed: The Lamb of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> without our aſſiſtance, cannot open the book of a ſinners conſcience, to take away from it the impreſſions of ſin. This is the imperious language of the Popiſh Prieſts to their Penitents; they deal with them in this manner; their Miſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary and Itinerary Preachers are yet more cruel to ſuch as are at their mercy: I would not have any man think that I add more than is true, I will aſſure him that I ſpeak nothing but what I know to be too true. If the Father-Confeſſors ſpeak not theſe words always, they have them in their thoughts, ſeeing that they deal thus with the people, and maintain that they muſt do ſo: So impertinent and ridiculous they are.</p>
               <p>But conſider in what manner this Confeſſion is made. They begin by a repetition of the <hi>Confateor,</hi> ſaying, <hi>I confeſs my ſelf to God the Father Almighty, to the Bleſſed Virgin</hi> Mary, <hi>to St.</hi> Michael <hi>the Archan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,</hi> &amp;c. What an impertinency is this! Doth my abſolution depend upon the will of God the Father, of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> of St. <hi>Michael,</hi> and of the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:95424:55"/>Prieſt equally, muſt they all conſent to the forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of my ſins? is not God's mercy ſufficient alone? why do they rank them with God? Afterwards the Prieſt forceth them to mention all their ſins, every particular, and circumſtance; asking them queſtions according to the condition of the perſons, but ſuch many times as are more proper to teach than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove vice, daily experience declares. But what manner of ſins think ye that the Penitents are forced to confeſs? Such as many times are but the whim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of the ghoſtly Fathers, who would perſwade their Zealots of being more ſpiritual and more ſubtil than ordinary by this means, to oblige them to a greater reverence of their perſons. What ridiculous impertinencies have ſome of theſe Father-Confeſſors taught their penitent Nuns, in their Confeſſions: You ſhall ſee what the right reverend Father, Father <hi>Yves</hi> a <hi>Capuchin</hi> of <hi>Paris,</hi> hath written in his Letters of <hi>Agathon</hi> to <hi>Eraſtus,</hi> and Father <hi>Chiron</hi> a <hi>Carmelite,</hi> in his Book called <hi>The Examen of the Myſtical Theology.</hi> They bring a devout Nun before her Father-Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſor, accuſing her ſelf in this ridiculous manner and nonſenſical language: <hi>Benedicite,</hi> ghoſtly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>I accuſe my ſelf, and confeſs that I have not been early enough upon my tip-toes, in the heart, and about the concerns of my internal houſwifery; in the time of my prayer I have not been fixed to the In-action, nor to the contem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plation of the In-being, I have not acted my devotions in a fit</hi> temperies <hi>of ſoul and body, I have ſuffered my ſenſes to wander from the domination of the Man-ſpirit; thus hath it been almoſt all the time of the aeconomical work of my obediential duty; I have eaten and drunk, and ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of the creature too freely, otherwiſe than in ſight of
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:95424:56"/>natural mercy, without minding in due time to do acts of stop, ſtop to my All, by a recal of my ſelf within my ſelf, of my outward part within the compaſs of my inward, in the bottom of my ſoul: I have not done my beſt endeavour to keep my ſelf always in the fiery Meridian of the full reigning of God in me; I have not reſted my ſelf under the caliginous mists of the enlightning Pedagoge: I have not been thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful enough to the triple Spirit of God in me, to the tear-heart, the endure-God, and the tranſpiercing lover-God.</hi> Theſe two Authors affirm that the Miſſionary Prieſts of <hi>Peter Camus</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>Bellay,</hi> and Father <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natian</hi> have taught their devout Nuns to confeſs their ſins in this extravagant manner. Let any man judge if ſuch leſſons as theſe are not ridiculous and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent; if their conſciences are not deceived, by be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving all theſe niceties to be crimes; they had better declare with <hi>David, I have ſinned,</hi> I acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge my offence, O God have mercy upon me, than to run over ſo many ſidle-fadles. The time of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion is ſpent in reckoning up ſuch impertinencies as theſe; and after all, the Prieſt enjoyns a penance more ridiculous than the confeſſion it ſelf. A cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Monk informed me of a very diſcreet and vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Lady, who was ſo conſcientious, that ſhe came to him to intreat him to mitigate or change a penance commanded to her by a Miſſionary Prieſt, which was to dip her ſmock in cold water, before ſhe went to bed, and to ſleep in it every night for a whole year; ſhe had been once obedient to him, but her obedience almoſt coſt her her life. Nevertheleſs ſhe was per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded that there was no ſalvation for her if ſhe did not perform her penance, this caſt her into a deſpair, and made her almoſt mad. See unto what grievous
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:95424:56"/>follies and miſtakes this ſuppoſed power drives the <hi>Papiſts:</hi> They pull Jeſus Chriſt from his throne, to place their Prieſts in his ſeat; they enſlave the ſouls and conſciences of men to their wills, ſo that they believe themſelves bound to credit whatſoever they ſay, to do whatſoever they command, yea the greateſt follies and impoſſibilities.</p>
               <p>§. Abſtinence and Faſting I have always look'd upon as a very holy and uſeful practice; but I could never underſtand, under this diſpenſation of God's Grace, in this liberty and freedom from all laws that are not of his enacting, how it is poſſible, that a good piece of beef, or a ſlice of fat bacon ſhould be able to damn my ſoul, ſooner than a red herring. For we are commanded by St. <hi>Paul, to eat that which is ſet before us;</hi> and our Saviour aſſures us, <hi>that it is not that which enters into the mouth that defiles the ſoul, but that which comes out.</hi> They tell us that <hi>Moſes, Elias,</hi> and our Saviour Chriſt have done ſo before us; their virtuous examples in this reſpect were admirable, but not imitable; the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are not careful to follow them exactly, no more than the <hi>Protestants:</hi> For they ſhould ſpend forty days and forty nights without eating or drinking. I am perſwaded that if the Pope ſhould make any ſuch law, the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Biſhops and Cardinals would never believe that he was inſpired of God. But we may ſee by experience, that abſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nence from meats and faſtings are quite out of fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, and ſeldom obſerved by the <hi>Roman</hi> Catholicks; their Caſuiſts allow liberty to ſo many, that but few
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:95424:57"/>in theſe days think themſelves to be obliged to keep theſe Laws; for if you pleaſe to ſet aſide all Women with child, all wet Nurſes, all Handy-crafts-men, Plow men, Mariners and Seamen, Servants that work all day, all Travellers, weak and ſick, ſuch as have no means to eat a good meal, that is to ſay, ſuch as have no fiſh, or ſomething like that for their dinner; ſet aſide the Magiſtrates, and others, that labour with their brains, the Ladies, that cannot ſleep without a good ſupper in their bellies, and ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally all ſuch as have not attained to the Age of one and twenty, I or that are above threeſcore; and tell me, how many will remain? And of thoſe whom we have not mentioned, but very few obſerve fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, for it is no faſting to feed twice a day. I am certain, they are rather guilty of gluttony, to fill their paunch above meaſure at noon, that they might not long for meat the reſt of the day. I think they had better never have made any ſuch Law, which concerns ſo few, and which by them is very ill obſerved. But the Prince of Darkneſs hath found out this expedient, to beget doubts and ſcruples in the ſouls of men, that they might ſin againſt their miſtaken conſciences, and by that means run into damnation.</p>
               <p>I muſt take notice here of another conſideration, unto which I could never find any ſatisfactory an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, and which hath help'd me to diſcover the vanity of all theſe feigned auſterities, whereof the obſervation is no ſmall hinderance to a true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian mortification, a ſubduing of our paſſions and unruly luſts. If our perfection in Chriſtianity, and the holineſs of our Souls, depends ſo much upon fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting,
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:95424:57"/>abſtinence, and ſuch mortifications of the body, the <hi>Phariſees</hi> were good <hi>Christians,</hi> and the <hi>Turks</hi> would deſerve a greater eſteem of holineſs than we; for the <hi>Phariſees</hi> did perform all theſe things ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly, and the Laws of the <hi>Turks</hi> forbid them to drink wine, and to forbear eating of ſeveral meats all their life time, beſides they have certain Monks very auſtere in their living, the <hi>Derviſes</hi> whip them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves publickly in the ſtreets, they cut their skin with ſharp raſors, and ſuffer many ſuch cruelties in their bodies, as <hi>Calcondile</hi> and <hi>Michael Baudier</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late. The wilfull penances of our Monks are not to be compared to theirs. We may therefore con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, and ſpeak confidently, that this Law is as great an hypocriſie and abuſe, as the other Inventions of the <hi>Papiſts.</hi> To make our Chriſtian perfection conſiſt in ſuch niceties and follies, is to catch at the ſhadow inſtead of the body, to miſtake the colour for the ſubſtance, the appearance for the reality, the ſhell for the pearl, and the night for the day: But ſuch as are inveigled by the peruſal of the Popiſh Books, which are only allowed to be read in that Church, and ſuch as are beſotted and deceived by the repeated leſſons of their Preachers, who ſeldom cry up any thing elſe in their Pulpits, cannot well make all theſe reflections and conſiderations.</p>
               <p>§. The unlawfulneſs of the Prieſt's Marriage is a Law contrary to the Holy Scriptures, and the cauſe of many abominations, and of the damnation of many Souls, which might otherwiſe be ſanctified and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:95424:58"/>What I ſhall ſay concerning this matter, may be applied to the Monks and Nuns. Jeſus Chriſt himſelf hath approved of Nuptial Solemnities and Marriage by his preſence. He doth in no caſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allow it. <hi>Marriage,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>is honourable amongst all men, Heb.</hi> 13.4. Virginity it is true cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth us to be very like the Holy Angels, nevertheleſs the ſame Apoſtle aſſures us, that <hi>it is better to marry than to burn,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. The Examples of the Apoſtles, and of their Succeſſors, ſhould be ſufficient in my judgment to anſwer all the objections that may be invented; for although our virtue be never ſo extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary, and God's Grace in us be never ſo power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, it is a grievous preſumption to affirm, that we have more virtue and grace than the Apoſtles had, more than thoſe illuminated Souls, full of the moſt wonderful perfections. It is to no purpoſe, that they extoll what the Holy Scripture and the Primitive Fathers have ſaid in praiſe of Virginity. Children that know not what it is to engage in a vow, to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that which depends more upon God than upon our ability, may approve of their reaſons, but we cannot allow them. If we did all but underſtand, as I have done by the confeſſions of many perſons, how many horrid and enormous crimes this Vow hath occaſioned in the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> It fills it with abominations and filthineſs, and cauſeth ſuch as ſhould be examples of holineſs to be paterns of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of vices.</p>
               <p>Virginity, I confeſs, is praiſe-worthy, I have not changed my Opinion in relation to that: I remember very well what I have read upon this ſubject in St. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> St. <hi>Auſtin,</hi> and in other Fathers, who
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:95424:58"/>have employed their eloquent pens to ſet forth the praiſes of theſe noble virtues, if we may ſo ſtile things that are in themſelves indifferent. The ſame Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons that I have preached in <hi>France</hi> in praiſe of a ſingle life, I dare preach in <hi>England,</hi> without fear of reproof. But I could never yet find in all the Holy Scripture, nor in the writings of the Fathers of the Church, any thing that ſhould oblige us to engage in this raſh Vow; or that it is a virtue which we may promiſe to our ſelves to obſerve and keep faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully till death: I cannot find that God ever promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to beſtow the graces neceſſary for the obſervation of this vow, to all that ſhall undertake it. After a long experience and acquaintance with the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of men, I have underſtood ſufficiently that this vow of perpetual Virginity engages ſome in the commiſſion of grievous abominations, who might otherwiſe be Saints.</p>
               <p>Therefore I am forced to condemn this Law, as one of the moſt wicked inventions of the Devil in Chriſtianity, and one of the moſt dangerous of all his ſnares: I dare not ſay all that I know of this mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, if I did, I ſhould force every modeſt Reader of theſe few lines to bluſh; for I might declare not only ſinful thoughts, or deſires, and wicked deeds cauſed by this vow, ſo highly eſteem'd as a virtue, theſe are but natural brats of that deviliſh father; but I might mention unto you the moſt fearful monſters, actions, crimes, and unheard of abominations pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from it, ſuch as deſerve the fire of God's ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance from heaven, which once fell upon <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> ſuch as deſerve that the earth ſhould ſwallow us up alive, but God will not puniſh the
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:95424:59"/>innocent with the guilty. How many crimes have been acted! bloody murders and ſecret cruelties per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petrated! If <hi>Tertullian</hi> were now alive, he might with as good reaſon exclaim againſt the promoters of this law, as once he did againſt <hi>Marcion,</hi> who attempted to hinder the begetting of children. He compared that wicked man to <hi>Herod,</hi> and ſaith, that in his opinion he was more criminal than <hi>Herod,</hi> for that Tyrant cut the throats of children already born, but <hi>Marcion</hi> was guilty of a greater cruelty, becauſe he did endeavour to hinder the generation of infants. The Promoters of a Single life amongſt the Prieſts are guilty of the ſame heinous offence; they are guilty of <hi>Herod</hi>'s cruelty, <hi>Marcion</hi>'s barbarity, the <hi>Gnoſtick</hi>'s murders: All this they cover with the ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow of a pretended virtue; they deſtroy many ſouls by engaging them in an eſtate where it is almoſt impoſſible that they ſhould obtain ſalvation; and cauſe them to commit many anticipated murders and cruelties. Whoſoever hath been where I have, ſeen what I have beheld, and heard what I have heard, ſhall ſay the ſame as I do now. I have many times pitied thoſe poor fouls that have revealed unto me their ſecrets in relation to what I ſpeak: How mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable, ſaid I, is this poor man! if it were not for this one thing he would live like a Saint; all his confeſſion is ſtuffed with nothing elſe but with the ſins againſt his vow; that excepted, I find his deſires are zealous, he is devout in prayer, religious in his behaviour, exemplary in his life and converſation: and becauſe he cannot make uſe of that remedy which God hath allowed to the reſt of men, as a prevention of ſin, he is in inevitable danger of damnation, if God
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:95424:59"/>don't hinder him by his wonderful mercy. If theſe lines happen to come into the hands of a Prieſt of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, I am perſwaded, that in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience he cannot blame me for what I now write, nor will he think that this is a ſtayrical Libel, or that theſe are unjuſt or ill-grounded accuſations; for who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever hath been a Father Confeſſor amongſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> knows an hundred times more than I dare reveal. He knows, that the greateſt vice of Prieſts is the breach of their Vow, and that this is ſuch an ordinary ſin amongſt them, that a Prieſt is look'd upon as a notable Saint, if he be never guilty of other ſins but of drunkenneſs, and if he can com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand his unruly ſelf ſo much for a week only, ſo as not to let a lecherous thought eſcape towards a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man. At leaſt if they would allow a time ſufficient to to try our own ſtrength, and to experience the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of God's Grace within us. But far from this, they determin their Children to the Cloiſter, while they are yet in the Cradle: The eldeſt Son, as is moſt uſual, being deſigned for Marriage; the ſecond muſt be a Knight of <hi>Malta;</hi> the third appointed for a Church-man, into whoſe hands they often thruſt the Breviary before he can yet pronounce the Title of the Book, and complement him with the reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſtile of Abbot, while he is as yet un-acquainted with his Alphabet, and what reluctancy ſoever he ſhall hereafter have againſt it, yet muſt he neceſſarily ſtill continue an Eccleſiaſtick. But if the elder Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther chance to fail, the Vocation then ceaſeth, and the Spirit (that <hi>bloweth where it liſteth</hi>) ſeems to have with drawn its influence, he throws of his purple robe, and the Gentleman, who was but ſince
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:95424:60"/>yeſterday changed from a Clergy-man, is now as rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy for the Nuptial as he was before for the Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious Vow; and all this (ſay they) proceeds from God, which thoſe may believe that think fit, but I for my part never could. As for the Daughters, if there happen to be three, they do uſually enter two of them into the Covent; and here it is obſervable, that God is wont to call the moſt deformed, whilſt the other is born for the enjoyments of the world. The Peaſants indeed do cauſe their eldeſt Sons to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply themſelves to their ſtudies, but after they have performed their Exerciſes, and ſpent a conſiderable ſum in their Education, it is no longer at their choice, whether they will become Prieſts or not, but are compell'd to it, for fear of incurring the diſpleaſure of their Parents. Thus it is, that they betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the practice of this Law, and from hence proceed ſo many diſorders, which might eaſily be prevented, if the Church were left to its primitive liberty.</p>
               <p>But that which makes theſe Conſtitutions of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> to ſeem unto me the more ſtrange and extravagant, is this, that they commonly prefer them to the Commandments of God. Let a young man have given himſelf over never ſo much to the ſin of the fleſh, yet when he comes to take Holy Orders, this ſhall create no neceſſity of taking out a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſation; but if he ſhall chance to have married two wives, or but one, if ſhe hath been married before to another man, (which they call <hi>Bigamy,</hi>) this woman being dead, he cannot take Orders without a Diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation from the Pope, for which he muſt pay ſauce. Although a man ſhould never ſo often have taken the
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:95424:60"/>Name of God in vain, and uttered a thouſand blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemies; yet even for ſuch offences will any Prieſt very readily give his abſolution, and he ſhall be freed from his guilt and penalty by putting himſelf to the charge of two or three Maſſes: But if he ſhould at any time in <hi>Lent</hi> happen to eat a morſel of fleſh, there is no abſolution to be obtained for ſuch a crime, but from the hands of the Biſhop, who will inflict ſo ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere a penance, that he ſhall have cauſe to remember it all the reſt of his life. Let a woman be never ſo notoriouſly guilty of fornication, and proſtitute her ſelf as often as <hi>Lais</hi> or <hi>Meſſalina,</hi> there is no Confeſſor ſo inconſiderable but can give her an abſolution: But if by extraordinary misfortune ſhe ſhall on a Friday have taſted but one ſpoonful of ſoupe which was left the day before, ſhe muſt neceſſarily apply her ſelf to the Biſhop, and ſhall (if it be poſſible) be ſent to the Pope himſelf. By theſe means it comes to paſs that ſuch diſorders have crept into the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, and that at preſent they prefer humane laws to the Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of Almighty God</p>
               <p>§ Before I conclude, it is neceſſary to anſwer an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, that the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> are wont to make to any perſon that ſhall upbraid them with the abuſes and diſorders whereof we have before treated. Whence proceeds it then (ſay they) that there are ſo few per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that forſake the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion? and that in lieu of thoſe few that go over to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> party, we ſee great numbers return to the boſome of the Church, and make, as they call it, their Recantation,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:95424:61"/>whereas of all thoſe that have abandoned the <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant</hi> Religion, we ſee ſcarce any that return unto it after they have once forſaken it? To this I might anſwer ſeveral ways, and I could give many particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar reaſons, why ſeveral <hi>Proteſtants</hi> in <hi>France</hi> of great worth and quality have ſhifted their Religion, which is there no longer in faſhion, and accommodated themſelves to that of the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi> I ſhall only ſay this in general, which may be obſerved in the caſe of every particular perſon; that it is Intereſt, which firſt invites, and then detains them: this is that which firſt cauſeth them to change, and then obſtinately to adhere to what they have embraced.</p>
               <p>They act many things againſt the dictates of their conſcience to avoid a private perſecution, which is often more ſevere than that which is more open and avowed. The Charges which they offer, the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferments which they beſtow upon perſons of Quality, on condition that they ſhall change their Religion, and a Penſion of a thouſand Crowns promiſed to a Miniſter, provided that he quits his Party; are very powerful motives and arguments for the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church; and I have often admired at ſuch as could reſiſt ſo great Temptations. A Lady of quality, whil'ſt as a Meſſenger ſent from God I ſollicited and exhorted her to acts of Charity and compaſſion, cauſed me once to make an offer of 8000 Franks to a Maid-ſervant of the Reformed Religion, (and at ſuch a time as ſhe had received ſome ill uſage from her Miſtreſs) to try if I could by that means make her become a Proſelyte. I attempted it with all the Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torick and Philoſophy that I could make uſe of for ſuch a purpoſe, but ſhe ſtill remained conſtant, and
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:95424:61"/>ſlighted us both for the vanity of our attempt. This is no common virtue, and I believe there are few ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Religion in this City, but might be prevail'd with by ſo conſiderable a reward. But it is not by ſuch means as theſe that we ought to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour the converſion of our Brethren; but by the principles of conſcience, and the more rational mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives to ſalvation.</p>
               <p>On the other ſide, thoſe that are acquainted with the Reaſons that retain the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> in the Religion which they profeſs, will not wonder that there are ſo few of them made Proſelytes: They know well enough that the Nobility and the Commonalty, the Learned and the Unlearned, the Zealots and the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertines have an hundred inviſible chains by which they are held faſt. Never expect that a rich Abbot of 5000 Livres <hi>per ann.</hi> ſhould quit ſuch a preferment to become a Miniſter, or that a man in favour at Court ſhould incur the diſpleaſure of his Prince, by renoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Pope. Nor can you with any more reaſon hope for the converſion of the Learned: for you muſt look upon them in their Schools as Diſciples to no other but <hi>Ariſtotle;</hi> for they learn to diſpute before they are taught to believe, and become Philoſophers before they are Chriſtians: If at any time they read the Holy Scripture, it is not with any intent to ſatisfie themſelves which doctrine is moſt agreeable to that divine Rule; but that they may find therein ſome Text or other to be wreſted in favour of themſelves and their perverſe opinions. I read the Scripture my ſelf for a long time with this very deſign: when I met with any thing in it different from my prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, I thought my ſelf obliged to encounter it, and
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:95424:62"/>applied my ſelf forth with to the finding of Arguments which might ſerve as an anſwer to it: And this is that which renders the converſion of the Learned ſo difficult: nor is that of the Ignorant any leſs; for theſe are the people that will have no other Faith but that which they depoſite with their Curate, and yet ſo great an abhorrence for all ſuch as follow not their ſuperſtitions; that come not to Maſs, carry not their Roſaries about them, make no uſe of the Office of the Virgin, nor pray to other Saints, that they are always ready to attempt their extirpation, and believe that they ſhould therein do God good ſervice. I have here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore my ſelf had ſuch unchriſtian intentions and deſires as theſe wherewith the <hi>Papiſts</hi> are imbued, and amongſt the reſt thoſe of the Order of the <hi>Jeſuits.</hi> I became once ſo tractable a Scholar by the charitable inſtructions of theſe Maſters, that I was one of the firſt that rais'd the Tumult at <hi>Rennes,</hi> and ſet fire to a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Church, at ſuch time as it was believed that they were immur'd within it: and theſe reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Fathers were ſo far from diſcountenancing the outrage, that they declared their ſorrow and regret that we had not at leaſt burnt the Miniſter there alive. Judge therefore if there be any hopes of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion, who from their Cradle have imbibed ſuch ſentiments as theſe. But the Zealots are yet further removed from it, being blinded, and kept cloſe to their Principles by erroneous Maxims and ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious Principles, in which they are made to believe the truth and purity of the Chriſtian Religion to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt. They perſwade them, that they muſt at a ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture believe what the Church believes, that is, what their Director tells them, that they ought not to
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:95424:62"/>raiſe the leaſt diſpute about what is preach'd to them out of the Scripture, as being uncapable to compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend thoſe Myſteries; that to doubt in the leaſt of the truth of Miracles, Traditions, Indulgences; the Power of the Pope and his Prieſts, or to entertain the leaſt thought of the poſſibility of being ſaved in any other Religion, is a moſt enormous crime. So that that very light, which by the ſpecial favour of God is afforded them for their converſion, is look'd upon by them as a machination of the Devil, againſt which they are obliged to engage. This renders it in a manner impoſſible that they ſhould ever be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed. As for the Libertines, they have no thoughts of the well fare of their future ſtate, and therefore all Religions are to them indifferent, carrying al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways about them ſome pernicious principles, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they are provided, to combat againſt whatſoever ſhall oppoſe their ſenſual inclinations, and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with they extinguiſh the light of the Spirit, which is afforded them for their relief. Amongſt theſe I may rank the giddy and inconſtant, that out of a principle of Libertiniſm, abandon the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and a while after, upon the like motives, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to their former eſtate; a mercenary ſort of peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, that are ready to enroll themſelves in the ſervice of any that will hire them at a dearer rate. Such men as theſe, having inconſiderately ſhut themſelves up in a Cloiſter, where they are obliged to lead a regular life, grow quickly weary of their firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign, the Cowl is burdenſom to them, and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Yoke becomes inſupportable; hereupon they fancy, that if they ſally out, and go over to the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Party, they ſhall be received after the ſame
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:95424:63"/>manner that they are wont to entertain the revolting Miniſters in <hi>France,</hi> who are uſually complemented like Princes. With ſuch imaginations as theſe, and without any other motive, or being able to render any ſolid reaſon of their actions, one of them pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents himſelf to a Conſiſtory, which they preſume to be with a good intention, and being unwilling to be ſo injurious as to ſend him back, they receive him, in hope that he is ſincere in his profeſſion, and will prove a good man; nor is the aſſiſtance of ſome charitable perſons wanting: But the man, finding himſelf free from all ſubjection, begins to give the reins to his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate appetite, frequents Brothel-houſes, and gives himſelf over to a ſcandalous and ſenſual life; here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon they ſummon him to the Conſiſtory, that he may have the puniſhment inflicted on him which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, the charity lately extended to him is with-held, and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> again, by their ſollicitations, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of a Diſpenſation from <hi>Rome</hi> for the future, and an Act of Oblivion for what is paſt, they aſſure him of all poſſible incouragement, and thereby prevail with him to return to his former ſtate, without any conviction wrought upon his conſcience, or any other true motives of his change, than the inconſtancy of his mind, and his propenſity to his luſts and pleaſures. We need not marvel then, that ſuch as theſe ſhould forſake the communion of the true Church, ſince we ſeem hereby the rather to be confirmed, that that Church is the true Church from which they revolt, according to their own argument, which infers the holineſs and good diſcipline of a Religious Order from the number of ſuch as do renounce it. <hi>They went out from us,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>John, Ep.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 2.19. <hi>but they were not of
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:95424:63"/>us, for if they had been of us, they would have remained with us, but they went out, that they might be made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that they were not all of us.</hi> By their works we may judge of the ſincerity of their conſcience, and the truth of their faith, <hi>as the goodneſs of the tree is judged by its fruit.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>§. There are ſeveral other things, which from my own experience I could ſpeak to, in laying open the Abuſes of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, which I have not at preſent thought neceſſary to mention. But I am perſwaded, that what I have ſaid already may be ſufficient to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince you, that I have not without good reaſon for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> that I might embrace the Religion of the Church of <hi>England.</hi> I will conclude therefore, with my requeſt to you, that you would reflect on what I have done and ſaid: I have not I hope in this act of mine, diſcovered any thing of blind ignorance, or any unruly paſſion, which I truſt I may ſay with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out vanity, for by the grace of God I am free from it. I know very well, that I am rather expoſed to the pity than to the envy of the world, but this I have done that I might give glory to God, and aſſert that which I am perſwaded is the truth.</p>
               <p>All that I have ſaid concerning the Abuſes of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Church, are things whereof I am very well aſſured, and ſuch as I have not without a great deal of ſtudy and induſtry diſcovered: I have for ſix or ſeven years diligently ſearch'd for Reaſons, whereby I might defend them; ſometimes applying my ſelf to the Holy Scripture, ſometimes to the ancient Fathers and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:95424:64"/>Authors: I ſometimes ſeriouſly propoſed my Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections to a great number of moſt accompliſh'd men, with whom I had been long converſant, and never could receive any ſatisfactory return. Wherefore after all theſe Eſſays, being perfectly convinced of the truth of your Religion, I am conſtrain'd to renounce the Religion of my Anceſtors, and to take up a reſolution to forſake it. But how? and at what time? I muſt to the glory of God acknowledge it, that it was at ſuch a time as there was not the leaſt probability that I ſhould attempt it, for certain reaſons which ſome are not unacquainted with, and which are not fit to be publiſhed.</p>
               <p>It will be ſufficient to declare in general, that I have forſaken Popery in a time in which I had the ſtrongeſt and natural engagements to keep me in my predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors Religion, and in my former Profeſſion. How ſo? Becauſe a change muſt needs cauſe me to run many hazards, bring upon me the hatred of my Friends, and the diſpleaſure of my Kindred, make me appear to them as a declared Rebel, and an Apoſtate: So that according to the Laws of the Land that I have forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, I am to be puniſhed in an exemplary manner, for embracing the truth. Theſe and the following Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderations did long retard my deſign; as that by this alteration I ſhould purchaſe to my ſelf nothing but miſery, and in the judgment of ſome, the eſteem of a vagabond, or of a licentious perſon, guilty of ſome offence or ſcandal; and that I muſt never expect to be entertained and live in the world, but as little better than a Beggar.</p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding all theſe obſtacles and Panick fears, my Chriſtian Brethren, you ſee that I have freely
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:95424:64"/>and confidently engaged my ſelf in the profeſſion of your Religion: I forſake without regret or apprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions that of my Forefathers to embrace the <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> This act ought to be look'd upon, as an encouragement of ſuch as are doubting and wavering in their minds, whether that which they profeſs is the beſt and the fureſt, without doubt it is. You may believe me upon my word, which I have confirmed by my deeds, for God be praiſed in this matter I am not ignorant, I have been long enough deliberating and weighing the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of both Parties, of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> and <hi>Papiſts;</hi> I know from whence I come, what I forſake, and what I embrace. Beſides, you may well look upon and eſteem me to be no mad man, that runs wilfully into his own damnation. There is none more careful in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> than I am, to avoid the cauſes of damnation: If I did but doubt of my ſalvation in the Reformed Religion, or if I could believe that it were poſſible for me to be ſaved in the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> I here ſwear and proteſt unto you, before God, that I would never do what you ſee I have done, I would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther undergo the moſt bitter torments, and whatever might happen to me, I would never wrong my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. This conſideration therefore, and my ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, ſhould ſettle and confirm every one of you in the Proteſtant Religion, ſhould appeaſe the troubles and doubtings of your mind, fix your reſolutions in the profeſſion of the Truth. And you, my beloved Brethren, that are ſufficiently grounded in your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and whoſe lives are conformable, my example ſhould oblige you to rejoyce, in that God is pleaſed to grant your private and publick requeſts, and the prayers of your Congregation, by ſending to you,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:95424:65" rendition="simple:additions"/>from time to time, Proſelytes, and bringing into your Flook the ſtraying Sheep, or rather the loſt Sheep, ſuch whereof the ſalvation was ſo difficult, that there was ſcarce any appearance or likelihood that it ſhould be brought to paſs. St. <hi>Anstin</hi> was named <hi>the ſon of</hi> Monica<hi>'s tears,</hi> becauſe his religious Mother ſhed ſo many, that at laſt ſhe obtained her requeſt, and her Son's converſion, from God's goodneſs. I may this day ſtile my ſelf in the ſame manner, for I look upon my ſelf as the return of your religious and charitable prayers, and the Son of your ſighs and tears. I would therefore now expreſs unto you my hearty thanks, but you deſire that I ſhould render them only to God. I have nothing elſe to requeſt from you, but the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of the ſame prayers for all thoſe whom I yet leave behind me, eſpecially for ſuch as I have confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in their errours and miſtakes; help, and joyn with me in my duty, in endeavouring their conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion. But eſpecially I muſt entreat your prayers to God, that I may for the time to come lead a life an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to that holy profeſſion, which I h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e this day made; that I may not be unworthy of your Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion here, and may attain with you hereafter to the fruition of that Crown of Glory, which God hath promiſed to his faithful Servants. To One God, and Three Perſons, the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, be aſcribed all Honour, Glory, and Praiſe, now and for evermore. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:95424:65"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
